<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lux veritatis or, Christian judicial astrology vindicated, and demonology confuted: in answer to Nath. Homes, D.D. Wherein his allegations of the learned, reasons, divine proofs, and arguments, are particularly examined and convinced. With the legality of the art maintained and warranted by Scripture. Whereunto is annexed, a short discourse of that great eclipse of the sun, March 29. 1652. By William Ramesey Gent. student in astrologie and physick.</title>
            <author>Ramesey, William, 1627-1675 or 6.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1341_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1351_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1341_1*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1351_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868032</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868032</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 177:E1341[1], 177:E1341[1*], 178:E1351[3], 178:E1351[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lux veritatis or, Christian judicial astrology vindicated, and demonology confuted: in answer to Nath. Homes, D.D. Wherein his allegations of the learned, reasons, divine proofs, and arguments, are particularly examined and convinced. With the legality of the art maintained and warranted by Scripture. Whereunto is annexed, a short discourse of that great eclipse of the sun, March 29. 1652. By William Ramesey Gent. student in astrologie and physick.</title>
                  <author>Ramesey, William, 1627-1675 or 6.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 138, [22] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.B. for Nath. Brooke at the Angel in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to:  Homes, Nathanael:  Dæmonologie and theologie.</note>
                  <note>"A short discourse of the eclipse of the sunne, on Monday, Martij 23. 1652" has separate dated title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy E.1341[1]: "March. 11th 1650"; imprint date crossed through; on Thomason E.1351[3]: "May 2".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678. --  Dæmonologie and theologie.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Demonology --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169799:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>X VERITATIS.</hi> OR, CHRISTIAN JUDICIAL Aſtrology VINDICATED, AND Demonology Confuted: In Anſwer to NATH. HOMES, D.D. Wherein his allegations of the Learned, Reaſons, Divine proofs, and Arguments, are particularly examined and convinced.</p>
            <p>With the legality of the Art maintained and warranted by Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is annexed, a ſhort Diſcourſe of that Great Eclipſe of the</hi> SUN, <hi>March</hi> 29. 1652.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM RAMESEY Gent. Student in Aſtrologie and Phyſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. B.</hi> for <hi>Nath. Brooke</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169799:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169799:2"/>
            <head>To all wel-willers and lovers of ART.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true, I may looke for (when I ſeriouſly conſider my own inſufficiency and lack of good utterance and a pleaſing oratorious phraſe) many cenſures, and be perplexed with doubts, whether I have or no choſen the better part; ſince moſt, or the generality of men are carried away ſooner with a pleaſing and deluding tongue, then truth, delivered in an homely or mean ſtile: eſpecially ſince this moſt noble ſtudy that I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
<pb facs="tcp:169799:3"/>
here to defend is ſo vulgarly traduced, and commonly both ill ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of: which indeed at the firſt, was ſome diſheartning to my underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings; yet becauſe my Antagoniſts Coat is ſuch, as that a word againſt <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> ſheltred under it, will by the vulgar be more heeded, then an Oration from another; and this noble Art in danger hereby to ſuffer (moſt falſely) an ill eſteeme in their opinions; for the well wiſhes I owe both to it, the truth, and all ye the ſtudents therein, and lovers of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whatſoever. I thought good rather to incur the harſh cenſure of ſome, then by my ſilence to give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the ignorant, and enemies thereof to vaunt themſelves againſt it: and truely notwithſtanding all this, I had not thus taken him up;
<pb facs="tcp:169799:3"/>
ſince neither he nor any one elſe can ſay ought againſt this ſcience but what hath been formerly moſt fully anſwered:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Looke</hi> Pirova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu, Goclenius, Bellantius, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſeallettes <hi>and Sir</hi> Chriſtoph. Heydon.</note> but for the Readers ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who perhaps would have concluded (had no body undertaken to anſwer him) he had been paſt anſwering. I very much fear there are many moſt groſſe faults and miſtakes in this Treatiſe, it being pen'd at that inſtant of time, I was more perplexed and troubled then in all my life before; my occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being ſuch, that I had no time to ſtudy a better method, or correct what hath eſcaped; it being the fruits of what my weake Genius did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in every houſe and place I came in (in purſuance of my then occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) where I could happily meet
<pb facs="tcp:169799:4"/>
with the leaſt occaſion. Yet my hope is, that in what I have been defective (as I doubt not but your piercing judgements will ſoon diſcover) you will both ſupport, ſupply and amend, hoping alſo ye will accept of the will for the deed: to whom I here Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate both my ſelf and weak labours to ſerve you to my weak power.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. RAMESEY.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die</hi> ☿ <hi>4. Decembris, 1650.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169799:4"/>
            <head>To the unpartiall READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS there is nothing more ridiculous amongst the learned, then to conclude, before a through underſtanding be, in the matter in queſtion and controverſie; ſo is there nothing more worthy or commendable in a man, then to be patient, and hear all, nay and indeed both tales, before judgement be given; for the old ſaying is, one tale is good till the other be heard; and if this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe be a thing beyond thy knowledge, I ſhould deſire thee firſt <hi>Legere, perlegere, &amp; tunc judicare,:</hi> Read, and read it over and over, before thou judge.</p>
            <p>This very ſame Art of <hi>Chriſtian Judiciall Aſtrologie</hi> which I here defend, being by the vulgar in general (ſome few years ſince) and alſo by ſome otherwiſe knowing and diſcreet, condemned as Illegal, Diabolical,
<pb facs="tcp:169799:5"/>
and indeed to be little better then Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft; I alſo as ignorant therein at that time as themſelves, concluded ſo too; yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an cccaſion one day, I deſired a Gentleman that was extream hot (in words onely) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, to do me the favour as to acquaint me with his knowledge of the unlawfulneſs thereof; that ſo I might have ſome ground for my then ill conceit thereof, as alſo to be better able to uphold my opinion; but to be ſhort, I could get nothing of conſequence out of him, that could any wiſe prejudice the validity of the Art; but onely he believed ſo; and how could any man tell him any thing that he knew not himſelf, without dealing with the Devil, or being a Witch? which (me thoughts) was ſo ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a man of judgement and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to have no better reaſons nor grounds for his high words, that I was even aſhamed I was of his opinion, and therefore thought it much more commendable to be ſilent thereafter in ſuch matters, which I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not; then to condemn an Art onely with words and no ſound argument.</p>
            <p>Whereupon being very much deſirous to
<pb facs="tcp:169799:5"/>
be ſatisfied in the verity and legality of this <hi>moſt famous Art of ASTROLOGIE,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Authors firſt induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the ſtudy of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</note> which ſo many diſcreet Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen would ſometime ignorantly condemn, I applied my ſelf to the ſtudy thereof, which after ſome expence of time and paines, I found to be ſo apparently true and lawful, that theſe flaſhes of my friends againſt it, was quickly manifeſt to me, proceeded meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from ignorance and tradition.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, Reader, that thou maiſt not in the leaſt be miſtaken herein, as the anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſts and enemies thereof are to condemn the Arts legality for the abuſe of the Artiſt, who will, out of vaine-glory and pride, often undertake to predict impoſſible things, <hi>I</hi> mean which this Art cannot reach unto; and ſo for their ſimplicity &amp; abuſe thereof, give occaſion to condemn that which of all ſtudies is the moſt <hi>delectable, comfortable, true</hi> and <hi>lawfull;</hi> not knowing indeed what it is, they would condemn, and ſo deceive both themſelves and reader.</p>
            <p>But that thou maiſt not herein be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; I ſay, I will here declare unto thee,
<pb facs="tcp:169799:6"/>
the whole power and ſubject of <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The whole power &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</note> and that firſt <hi>Negatively,</hi> and next <hi>Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Negatively,</hi> Firſt that the Rules of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie</hi> doth not meddle with vaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingents, or ſuch as have an indifferent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the oppoſites as depending upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, or indeterminate cauſes, which may happen one way or other.</p>
            <p>Secondly, mans will is not ſubject to the influence of the Stars, neither hath <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> to do with it, but accidentally, ſo far as the ſoul with the faculties thereof, follow the temperature of the body: neither doth Aſtrologie meddle with the providence of God;<note place="margin">Aſtrologers moſt falſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached to be ſearchers of the ſecrets of God.</note> or ſhew a cauſe of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, nor with the ſecrets of God; for <hi>they are paſt find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, ſaith the Scripture,</hi> Ergo, <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> that are but men that contemplate natural cauſes are falſly and moſt ſcandalouſly abuſed, when thus impeached.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, Aſtrologie, or the influence of the Stars, have no fatall neceſſity, except
<pb facs="tcp:169799:6"/>
ſome contingency be mixt therewith; for this were to deny the providence of God.</p>
            <p>But contrariwiſe, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> dealeth with ſuch things as are performed by Art and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with the will of man indirectly and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally; and his inclinations, tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and diſpoſitions, as alſo with his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and body, and with natural ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſes, and general accidents and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies; but if men will, contrary to the rules of Art, undertake to go beyond it, and abuſe both the Art and themſelves, ſhall any one therefore conclude poſitively it is unlawful, not efficacious or conſiſtent with ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon or truth? Sure thus to affirm, is as ſimple in any man, as for me to ſay Religion is Diabolical, falſe, frivolous, inconſiſtent with reaſon and truth, becauſe there are he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies crept therein, Schiſmes, and Sects.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I ſhall deſire all to whom this my weake and ſmall Treatiſe ſhall come, that they would not ſo inconſiderately and raſhly condemn what they underſtand not; but firſt, throughly weigh every particular ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and reaſon therein, before a cenſure proceed from their lips; yet I muſt be plain
<pb facs="tcp:169799:7"/>
with thee, I neither fear nor care for thy raſh concluſions; for ſince I know it will be acceptable to all impartial and judicious ſouls, I ſhall reſt content, ſince no man living can pleaſe all people. I ſhall be very glad if I have any whit been ſervicable to the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents herein, to whom I wiſh all proſperity, and could wiſh that all ingenious ſouls would apply themſelves, to the ſtudy thereof; which they may lawfully and ſafely do, for any hurt the antagoniſts thereof hath done it, for I do with all my heart love all thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to knowledge, and my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune is ſo much the more increaſed that I am acquainted with ſo few of the ſtudents of this noble Art of <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> to whom as alſo to thy ſelf, I wiſh all happineſſe, and remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy loving friend, W. RAMESEY.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die</hi> ☿ <hi>4. Decembris, 1650.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:169799:7"/>
            <head>The Contents of every Chapter and Section contained in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>IN Anſwer to his Diſtinctions, Deſcriptions, Obſervations and nature of Aſtrologie, wherein he is taught what Aſtrologie is, and his Diſtinctions and deſcriptions proved meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly erroneous, and convinced as malicious, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and inconſiſtent with reaſon or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty: or to ſay, <hi>ſus ſacerdos. Page</hi> 1.
<list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section.</hi> I.</label>
                     <item>Wherein is demonſtrated and taught the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of Aſtrologie. p. 1.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> II.</label>
                     <item>In anſwer to ſome cavils of Mr. <hi>Homes</hi>'s, wherein he denyeth Aſtrologie to be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Scripture, proved erronious and falſe. p. 4.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> III.</label>
                     <item>Proving Aſtrologie to be an Art. p. 13.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> IV.</label>
                     <item>Proving the lawfulneſſe of Aſtrologie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not impugned by Scripture, nor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels; but allowed of by the wiſeſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of men. p. 15.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> V.</label>
                     <item>Demonſtrating the antiquity of Aſtrologie p. 27.</item>
                     <label>
                        <pb facs="tcp:169799:8"/>
                        <hi>Section</hi> VI.</label>
                     <item>Shewing Aſtrology to be the profitableſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy revealed under the Sun to Mortals. p. 29.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>IN Anſwer to the opinions of the learned touching Aſtrologie, wherein is further ſhewn the legality of Aſtrologie, that the Stars are both ſignes and cauſes; and that Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his quoting the Fathers and learned, is meerly fallacious and envious, and no wiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to his intent and purpoſe. p. 37.
<list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> I.</label>
                     <item>Wherein is farther ſhewn, the legality of Aſtrologie, p. 38.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> II.</label>
                     <item>Wherein is ſhewn that the Stars are ſignes and cauſes. p. 39.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> III.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his Allegation againſt the ground of the Art is condemned, and his bringing St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> againſt it, proved fallacious, injurious and malicious; and how farre we ought to attribute to the power of the Stars. p. 46.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> IV.</label>
                     <item>Wherein Aſtrologie is defended againſt his Allegations, from Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi>'s words. p. 54</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> V.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his cavilling Mr. <hi>Briggs,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="tcp:169799:8"/>
are convinced. page 56.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>WHerein his divine proofs againſt Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, are examined and confuted. p. 59.
<list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> I.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his firſt Scripture proof, <hi>viz.</hi> Deut. 18. verſe 10. is convinced and cleared no wiſe condemn Aſtrologie. p. 60.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> II.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his ſecond proof is refelled, <hi>viz. Eſay</hi> 2.6. p. 69.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> III.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his third Text is convinced, <hi>viz. Eſay</hi> 44.25. p. 72.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> IIII.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his fourth proof is refelled, <hi>viz. Eſay</hi> 47.12, 13, 14. p. 77.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> V.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his fifth proof is proved weak, as to his purpoſe, <hi>viz. Ier.</hi> 10.2.3. p. 85.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> VI.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his ſixth poof is refelled, <hi>viz. Dan.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. p. 91.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>WHerein his reaſons and arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Aſtrologie, are particularly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and condemned, neither to conſiſt
<pb facs="tcp:169799:9"/>
with reaſon or truth. p. 95.
<list>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> I.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his firſt four-fold reaſon is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> II.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his objection touching the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of twins, is refelled, as alſo ſome other quirks againſt Aſtrologie examined and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced. p. 101.</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> III.</label>
                     <item>Wherein his indeavours to prove Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of no truth or certainty, as alſo it's rules and principles, are themſelves of leſſe truth or ground; nay, and indeed ſenſleſs. p. 113</item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Section</hi> IIII.</label>
                     <item>Wherein he thinketh the ground of the Art wholly ſhaken and overthrown, by affirming it meerly imaginary, <hi>viz.</hi> the ninth and tenth ſphear, and in them the Zodiack; therein proveth and ſheweth his own ignorance the more apparently manifeſt. p. 129.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>Wherein the confutation of the objections that are brought for Aſtrologie are examined, and refelled. p. 130.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169799:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>X VERITATIS. OR,</hi> Chriſtian judicial Aſtrology VINDICATED, In Anſwer to Doctor <hi>Nathaniel Homes.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> In anſwer to his Diſtinctions, Deſcriptions, Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, and nature of Aſtrologie. Wherein he is taught what Aſtrologie is, and his Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Diſtinctions proved meerely erroneous; and convinced as malicious, ignorant, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with reaſon or honeſty; Or to ſay, <hi>Sus ſacerdos.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section. I.</hi> The Definition of Aſtrologie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Reader may the better judge of the controverſie between Doctor <hi>Homes</hi> and my ſelf, I think beſt here before I enter upon any part of his diſcourſe, to ſet down what this Art of <hi>Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169799:10"/>
Aſtrologie</hi> is, which I undertake to defend. <hi>Ptolomie Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. Of his Quadripartite, defines it thus, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is that Art (joyning it with Aſtronomy, as making no difference betweene them, though Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> and other Adverſaries thereunto do) <hi>which teacheth by the motions, Configurations and Influences of the Signes, Starres and Coeleſtial Planets, to judge and prognoſticate of the natural effects and mutations to come, in the Elements and inferiour and Elementary bodies.</hi> And who ſo takes <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> to be any other thing, is altogether ignorant of the Art, or guilty of inveterate malice in traducing ſo noble and admirable a ſcience, eſteemed and allowed of in all ages, and that in great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and honour, as well as the ſtudents thereof (as in it's due place ſhall be made to appeare) by the chiefeſt and nobleſt of the people. Though Doctor <hi>Homes</hi> would faine perſwade the vulgar and ignorant ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that it is a Doctrin of Devils, &amp; unlawfull, which ſhall in it's due place be made to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare (as alſo the reſt of his weake arguments and cavils,) that they are meerely malicious, ignorant, weake, and inconſiſtent with reaſon or the thing in queſtion; which that he may not be ignorant of, as alſo for the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Reader, I doe here more plainly rehearſe by way of Quere, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, whether <hi>Astrologie</hi> or fore-telling,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169799:10"/>
or Prognoſticating by the Starres, be a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Art, free from all Diabolical practiſes and devices.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Whether <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> may not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be ſtudied and practiſed, by the beſt of Gods people, without offence in the leaſt, either to the law of God, or man (if they concur with the rules of the Scripture) which is the full matter in controverſie, and to be in this following diſcourſe diſcuſſed, handled and cleered; and if ſo, then certainly the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ignorant condemners of this <hi>Noble and moſt profitable Art ſtudied by mortals,</hi> (as in it's due place ſhall appeare) ought to be ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and that with examplary infliction, that poſterity may take warning how they condemne what they are ignorant of; and likewiſe be incouraged to apply their minds to the contemplation and knowledge of all Arts and Sciences, eſpecially this moſt heavenly and divine ſtudy of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> or the language of the Stars.</p>
                  <p>Now you have heard the diſtinction of <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> the ſubject intended, by it you may not onely ſee the cauſes which concur to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the nature of the Art, but alſo the finall cauſe, whereunto all the precepts of the Art are to be referred; ſeeing then the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the effects of the Starres in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and their bodies, dependeth of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169799:11"/>
Configurations, and Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Coeleſtial bodies,<note place="margin">Aſtronomy and Aſtrology both are one Art.</note> 
                     <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomy</hi> or <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> (for by the learned, there is made no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between them as ſeverall Arts, but gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conclude them (as indeed they are) one and the ſame Art) is divided into two parts, the firſt ſpeculative or theorical, which conſiſteth in the knowledge of the heavenly motions; the other part is that which conſiſteth in the effects and properties of the former motions, and without this <hi>(viz Aſtrologie)</hi> the other is meerly vaine and of no uſe, or to none or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe; the former <hi>viz. Aſtronomy</hi> furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> with matter and ſtuff where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to exerciſe himſelfe; the other <hi>viz. Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> diſpoſeth the matter, and accordingly judgeth as the caſe doth require, and therefore to be eſteemed the more noble part of this Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. II.</hi> In anſwer to ſome cavels of <hi>Mr.</hi> Homes his, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in be denyeth <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> to be warranted by Scripture, proved erroneous and falſe.</head>
                  <p>HAving thus painted forth the matter and forme of the thing intended to be inſiſted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169799:11"/>
on, I come now to ſhew you what Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his utmoſt power and malice againſt it is: and firſt his blind zeal begins to ſhew it ſelf, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading the Reader it is condemned by the Scripture, and no wiſe thereby tollerated; his words are, <hi>It is no where allowed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, under the notion of</hi> Aſtrologie, <hi>but every where ſpoken againſt as we ſhall ſee afterward:</hi> and all that he can ſhew us and make us ſee, is but ſix places of Scripture, which is farre from being worthy of the Title of a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, when there is none but knowes the extent of the Scripture to conſiſt of many halfe dozen Chapters, nay of books, <hi>Ergo</hi> not envy where condemned, and thoſe places nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but imagined by him to condemne <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> when indeed they ſerve no whit at all for his purpoſe, as in it's due place ſhall be made appeare. But he thinks theſe words to be of force enough, to aſtoniſh and diſcomfort the ignorant, from the ſtudy thereof; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as a warning peece, or that his other win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy reports may better take, and be more hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and beleeved, he prefixeth this ſlanderous and moſt falſe and wicked ſaying; and truly for his pollicy he is worthy applauſe, for miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting his words ſhould be little regarded, he colours them with a preface (as it were) of Religion;<note place="margin">Aſtrologie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of by Scripture.</note> yet this will not keepe him from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169799:12"/>
ridiculous to the wiſer and more learned ſort of people. But by the way, is it every where condemned? doth not the King and Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God, Pſal.</hi> 19.1. and in another place, <hi>The language of the Stars,</hi> (which is the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the language of the Stars; and is it not allowed any where in Scripture under the notion of <hi>Aſtrologie?) Is heard over all the earth, or the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt parts thereof, Pſal.</hi> 19.3. as if he had ſayd, there is no part free from the power of their Influences; for their power hath a general ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent over all Nations, Kingdomes, Countries, Provinces, and Languages. I pray, <hi>who can reſtraine the ſweet influences of the</hi> Pleiades? <hi>Job</hi> 38.31. <hi>And did not the Starres in their courſes fight againſt</hi> Siſera? <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.20. One of theſe places had been enough to have convinced him of great wickedneſſe, in denying the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth any where allow of Aſtrologie; for if he never read theſe places, then he is wicked, and no leſſe then wilfully wicked, to conclude what he underſtands not; if he hath peruſed them, then moſt malicious to ſpeak againſt truth; I may even as well ſay diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally wicked,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> himſelf rather to be imputed a teacher of the Devils Doctrin, then Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> and that he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth rather the Doctrin of Devils, for the Devils Doctrin is falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; and if he preacheth ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169799:12"/>
groſs lyes as theſe, he is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils preacher, and not Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, neither is Aſtrologie a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of Devils (as ſhall be made clear to him before the cloſure of my diſcourſe) as he in his 160 page, line 21. is pleaſed to terme it. So then, now I hope the Reader doth clearly ſee, theſe his firſt words of his diſcourſe, to be meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly envyous, ſlanderous, and malicious, (or at the beſt) moſt ignorant; for it will puzzle all his braines; and Mr. <hi>Raunces,</hi> nay and all that dare or will take their parts, to make any one of thoſe paſſages of Scripture (he brings to confute or condemne Aſtrologie) to ſerve in the leaſt for his turn, as in it's due place ſhall be cleared.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaith Mr. <hi>Homes, as other things that are naturall, which are brought to countenance</hi> Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, <hi>are not tollerated by the</hi> Encyclopedia, <hi>and general order and ſeales of all Arts and Sciences, within their own ſpheres, to be accounted</hi> Aſtrologie. For inſtance, Firſt, (ſaith he) <hi>Some urge that we know the tydes of the Sea, by the ſtate of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> and tempeſts by other Stars,</hi> which I am confident Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> cannot denye, but he will render himſelfe more ridiculous then already, which he indeavours to do thus; <hi>theſe and of the like nature, are properly handled in that part of natural Philoſophie, which we call</hi> Meteorologie; <hi>and ſo likewiſe are all fiery Meteors, Comets, &amp;c. and ſo by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169799:13"/>
conſequence are made an integral part of Phyſicks, for if you will ſay, becauſe of their external efficient cauſe,</hi> viz. <hi>the Starres; they are to be handled as a part of</hi> Aſtrologie, <hi>by the ſame reaſon there will be left no ſuch Science as natural Philoſophie, becauſe all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour bodies below the Moon (as ſayeth the great Philoſopher</hi> Ariſtotle) <hi>depend upon the ſuperiour Celestial bodies of the heavens.</hi> In all which he doth but ſhew his great miſtake in the ground of Aſtrologie, and his envy thereto; for how can Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> prove this is a meer urging, or an opinion of ſome, that the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is the cauſe of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea; or that it is rather to be attributed to that part of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophie, which is called <hi>Meteorologie,</hi> and ſo conſequently to be a part of Phyſicks, when all the world knows that hath any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience or underſtanding in Aſtrology, that he is as far from hitting the mark, as if he had miſt the Butt.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore for his better inſtruction, (for I ſee he is not ſo well verſt in Aſtrology as he pretendeth, or as one that is to condemne it ſhould be) I will make it appear to him, that the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is the abſolute cauſe of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea; and this is the opinion of all or moſt knowing and learned writers, both in this Art and other Sciences; and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but it is ſo clear to all the learned, that his great friend <hi>Picus Mirandula,</hi> which was a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169799:13"/>
ſtronger Champion (or at leaſt more knowing in the Art then he) againſt Aſtrologie, doth confeſs the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> to be the poſitive and ſole cauſe thereof.</p>
                  <p>And thus,<note place="margin">The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> the cauſe of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea.</note> if he have any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the Art (as by his writing, I muſt confeſſe (as I but now ſayed) I ſee none) let him take the true time of the Seas flowing firſt, and then obſerve in what part of heaven the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is accidentally, placed by her violent diurne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he ſhall find it to flow till ſhe come to an abſolute <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> aſpect of the place ſhe was in at it's firſt beginning to flow; and then will continue ebbing till ſhe come to the direct ☍ or oppoſite place in the heavens, &amp;c. Still let him obſerve exactly when ſhe comes to the <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ of the place of her firſt beginning, and he ſhall never erre in this point; this is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well known to the learned Practitioners, and the ſonnes of Art; yet note that ☉ and other Starres may haſten, hinder and alter the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> influence, as he may ſee at ☌ and ☍ of ☉ or the change and full, in ſpring tides, and neap tides, at quarters and half quarters. I would he had not been ignorant of this, and then perhaps, (this being the beginning of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) he had not undertook to lay pen to Paper againſt this moſt heavenly, moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and moſt contemplative, delectable ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169799:14"/>
and ſcience of the Stars and Coeleſtial bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. So by this time he clearly ſees how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate and raſh this his ſophiſtical and falſe argument is.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, ſaith Mr. <hi>Homes, others ſay that by Aſtrologie we know Eclipſes and Changes of the Moon; but we ſay Aſtronomy doth challenge this as belonging to it, &amp;c.</hi> My anſwer is, that I ſay, (what ever he telleth me others may or do ſay) he cannot but know that thoſe that ſay ſo are not verſed therein, and are as ignorant to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply or attribute this part of the practick, <hi>viz.</hi> Aſtrologie to the Theoricall part, <hi>viz.</hi> Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy; as he is to make a diſtinction between the one and the other, as two diſtinct Arts, when <hi>Ptolomie</hi> whom the moſt learned follow, in his book, chap. 1. of his <hi>Quadripartite</hi> (as above ſaid) defining Aſtrologie, maketh no diſtinction between the one and the other, but that the one is Theoricall, the other Practicall. And thirdly,<note place="margin">How doth he define (by all his rabble) the Art of Aſtrologie?</note> ſaith he, <hi>If any one urge that Aſtrologie bandles of the qualities and effects of the ſtars,</hi> we Reply, <hi>that ſo doth Aſtronomie, of their qualities namely, of their light and colour, and naturall Philoſophie of their effects, in watry, ayrie, and fiery meteors:</hi> as much as to ſay, Aſtrologie is no Science at all, but will give its property to another ſtudy; if this be not ſlanderous and malicious, let the weakeſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169799:14"/>
in the world judge: he might as well then all this while have called it, Natural Philoſophy, as Aſtrologie; and then he tels us, if we admit of the Title <hi>Alſted gives to Astrologie,</hi> viz. <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia planetaria,</hi> or Planetary Aſtrologie, and of Doctor <hi>Willets</hi> titles, <hi>viz. Astromaney &amp; Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethliaca;</hi> then ſaith he for concluſion by all obſerve, <hi>that there is no place left for Aſtrologie;</hi> by which he clearly renders himſelf the moſt malicious of all wretches, to deny that Art which above 298.<note place="margin">The learned and famous Sir <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> recordeth them, which you have verbatim by and by.</note> of the moſt wiſe men of all ages have ſtudied and practiſed (their names you ſhall have hereafter in its place;) both before and ſince Chriſts time, whoſe antiquity may be derived from our firſt father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> maintained by Princes and Kings, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced by that greateſt of worthies, <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great; and not condemned by any of the Fathers, or the practice thereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by the Church, farther then that they ſhould not hereby be drawn from the ſtudy of Divinity, as you ſhall ſee by and by; Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> me thinks being a wiſe man, ſhould not write againſt, (and that in ſuch a zealous manner) a thing which is not in <hi>rerum natura,</hi> or in <hi>poſſe,</hi> as in his firſt Section of his tenth Chapter, he ſtudies to make Aſtrologie appear, to what purpoſe then are all his arguments againſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169799:15"/>
when he will not admit of any ſuch thing in the world: what doth he write againſt then? and why doth he ſo much condemn the ſtudents thereof? becauſe he knows not the validity thereof; becauſe he knows not the rules and fundamentals thereof; becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he is altogether ignorant of the ſame; and let him not be angry I plainly tell him ſo, (plain dealing is beſt among friends) for if he did, he would have been ſo far from writing or ſpeaking againſt it, that he would have been more furious and hot with any one ſhould have condemned it, then I am with him; for he that will ſpeak againſt what he knoweth not, and bring falſe, ſcandalous and ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call arguments to maintain his opinion; he I ſay, would certainly terme that man no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a fool, or at the beſt a knave to write againſt what he knows, and can alſo prove to be true; but I will not be ſo hot with him.</p>
                  <p>But now that he may ſee his errour in offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to undertake to put men out of conceit with this heavenly ſtudy, I will ſhew him here (before I begin to anſwer his ſecond Section, in that which I have to ſay to it, though this will ſufficiently refel it.)</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that Aſtrologie is an Art.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the lawfulneſs of it, being not impugned by Scripture nor councels, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of by the wiſeſt and greateſt men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:169799:15"/>Thirdly, the antiquity of it.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, that it is the profitableſt ſtudy under the Sun.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Proving Aſtrologie to be an Art.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ARiſtotle, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Aſtrologie is proved an Art.</note> 
                     <hi>Phyſ.</hi> affirmeth that Aſtrologie is <hi>Scientia media,</hi> a Science between the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks and natural Philoſophy, for the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are meerly Mathematical, and in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice are applyed to ſenſible matter as the Phyſical ſubject thereof; moreover he ranks it alſo amongſt the liberal ſciences; and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexeth it to Philoſophy in ſuch a ſort, that he ſeemeth indifferent to uſe the name of a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher and an Aſtrologer for the ſame. So likewiſe <hi>Averroes</hi> in his Commentary on the 12. of the <hi>Metaphyſicks,</hi> text 44. ſpeaking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the power of the heavenly bodies, in the procreation and conſervation of all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, and in their mutuall conſent and and aſſiſting one another in their mutual ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, he reſembleth them to good gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in a Common-wealth, that joyntly concur in one unanimous conſent for order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame: His words are <hi>diſpoſitio in jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169799:16"/>
corporum coeleſtium ad invicem in creando en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, quae ſunt hic, &amp; conſervando ea, eſt ſicut diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio regentium bonorum, qui juvant ſe ad invicem in regendo bonam civitatem.</hi> And in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary on the ſecond book of Phyſicks, his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter, ſheweth that natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and Aſtrologie have one and the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and yet are diſtinguiſhed by a divers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; and in the third of the Metaph. Comment, 7. he affirmeth the knowledge of the Stars to be a Mathematical Art; and ſo it hath ever in all ages by the moſt learned Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers been eſteemed. I believe Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> nor no man elſe that knoweth any thing, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that it is one of the liberal ſciences, and if he wil condemn it as none, he muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to loſe one of them, which were to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf the eighth wiſe man; what ſcience I pray will he place in the room of it, ſince he thus indeavours to excommunicate it, for he tels us it is as meere a phanſie as <hi>Palmeſtry,</hi> and yet <hi>Galen</hi> (one of his learned, that he brings to condemn Aſtrologie with the word <hi>Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> that it is <hi>Sophiſtical,</hi> page. 115. l. 11.) as Phyſitians themſelves report, teacheth to know the temperature of the body by the palm of the hand; and his reaſon is, becauſe the mind commonly followeth the conſtitution of the body; thus you may ſee how he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth and catcheth at any thing that he thinks
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169799:16"/>
wil make in the leaſt for his turne; as alſo of <hi>Alſted,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Willets</hi> Titles of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, when the queſtion is, whether either of them knew the common rules of the Art. So then, this being made clear to him that it is an Art, and not onely ſo, but a Science, and hat one of the liberal Sciences; I come now to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond leſſon I promiſed him. <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Proving the lawfulneſſe of Aſtrologie, being not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned by Scripture, nor Councels; but allowed of by the wiſeſt and greateſt men.</head>
                  <p>WHat hath already above been ſayed, is clear to any judicious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial eye,<note place="margin">The lawfulneſſe of Aſtrologie.</note> that this Art is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, where I ſay, <hi>The heavens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the glory of God, &amp;c.</hi> But to clear it more plainly, the Pſalmiſt in his very next words ſayeth, <hi>The Firmament ſheweth the works of his hands, Pſal.</hi> 19.1. which is clear to me is meant thereby that he effecteth by them, (and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing) (though I muſt confeſſe there are divers interpretations thereof) my reaſon is, that otherwiſe, every thing which is created doth declare the handy work of God; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> wil find <hi>Aquinas</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:169799:17"/>
of my opinion: He hath heard alſo, that there is no ſpeech nor language, where the voice of the Stars are not heard; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.3. which may ſerve here again very wel for the purpoſe in hand;<note place="margin">God prohibiteth not the ſtudy of Aſtrologie.</note> and to ſpeak more plainly, that God doth not prohibite mortals from the ſtudy of them; you may ſee how the Holy Ghoſt by <hi>Stephen,</hi> in the 7. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> verſe 22. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the commendation of <hi>Moſes,</hi> giveth him (over and above the commendation that was aforeſaid) that he was learned <hi>in all the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Egyptians, and was mighty in words and deeds,</hi> which is cleare to any rational man, that if it had been any wiſe ſinful, diabolical, or odious in the ſight of God, <hi>Moſes</hi> would not have applyed his ſtudy thereunto; or at leaſt, it would never have been recorded in his praiſe. I might inſtance here <hi>Daniel, Solomon,</hi> and others, but this is ſo clear, that to inſiſt longer hereon, were but vaine, ſince there is no one place in the Scripture that can be ſhown to ſpeak poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively againſt Aſtrologie,<note place="margin">Aſtrologie noe wiſe condemned by the word of God.</note> or the ſtudy thereof, more then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member us not to give the glory of the Creator to the Creature, &amp;c. as in the anſwer to his divine proofes ſhall appeare. Wherefore then ſince it is warrantable and lawful out of Scripture to ſtudy this Art, nay
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169799:17"/>
and as we ſee by experience, warranted by God, in the ſhewing of blazing Stars to Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers only (not to the vulgar &amp; proficient in other Arts) to forewarn his people of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and puniſhment to come;<note place="margin">Looke my reply to <hi>Raunce</hi> his Declaration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Aſtrology</note> and if it were not ſo, he might as wel ſhew ſignes on earth to the illiterate, by common vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar things; as in heaven to the learned Aſtrologer, who onely can judge of their effects. Wherefore then I ſay, of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Art muſt be allowed of by Councels, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wiſer ſort of people, eſpecially by the godlier ſort of Councels, whoſe acts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations wil be grounded on piety and the word of God,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> and if otherwiſe, I value not what their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is; for they are but men, and (guided by their own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and opinions,<note place="margin">How farre the Councels in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages hath or may lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Aſtrologie.</note>) are but fraile, ſubject to infirmitie and error, <hi>humanum eſt errare,</hi> he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but know alſo that even the palpableſt truths have been condemned by Councels, either for ſome ſelf intereſt, or for abuſe of the thing condemned; as for inſtance, the Bacaran Councels (as wel as the Roman Senate) hath condemned Aſtrologers, but how? not becauſe they were ſtudents in that heavenly ſcience, but for truſting in Aſtrology
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169799:18"/>
(and who is ſo ſuperſtitious, may not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be termed an Aſtrologer, for Aſtrologers are in no ſort hereof guilty) the words of the Councel is in the <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. of <hi>Bacaran</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, <hi>Si quis animas, &amp; corpora humana fatalibus ſtellis credit aſtringi, ſicut pagani &amp; priſcillianus dixerunt, anathema ſit.</hi> Who ſo truſteth in the fatal neceſſity of the Stars, as the heathens and Priſcillianiſts do or ſay, let him be accurſt; to all which, there is no Aſtrologer, but wil wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly condeſcend; for by this, is not Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie nor Aſtrologers in the leaſt condemned, but the abuſe of the Art, to give that to it, which properly belongs to God the creator of theſe heavenly bodies; the decree is againſt thoſe that truſt in them, or beleeve a fatal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, not that ſtudy the knowledge of them, and make a true uſe of them. So likewiſe the Councel or Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> made a Law againſt thoſe that multiplied Gold and Silver, why? not becauſe they condemned that heavenly revelation, or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the <hi>moſt bleſſed Stone of the Philoſophers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">This is the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima mundi, Adrop. ☿ Philoſopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, leo veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> the life of the world, which that learned <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> ſaith, is actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and animal, created by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, found every where, knowne by few, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by none under it's proper name, but in figures and riddles.</note> but they forbad the multiplication of Gold and Silver, in that they thought it too great a treaſure for any private ſubject, and to prevent rebellion, commotions and inſurrections in the Common-Wealth, like
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169799:18"/>
wiſe Pilots ſitting at the ſterne, did ſtudy to prevent the ſtorme which was likely otherwiſe to ſhipwrack the ſafety thereof. So that I ſay then, there is no Councel, (if they have any ſpark of Religion, learning or policy) that will ſhew them ſelves ſo ridiculous, as to decree-any thing in the leaſt, againſt either Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or Aſtrologie, taking it as it is in it ſelf, and not abuſed; which is not the fault in the Art, but the Artiſt in going beyond the Art; for if under the colour of Aſtrologie, I ſtudy Necromancie, is Aſtrologie therefore to be condemned as unlawful, becauſe together with it I ſtudy unlawful Arts? No, ſure ſince this is a thing ſo far different; therefore it is good to put the Saddle on the right Horſe.</p>
                  <p>And this my argument is thus confirmed, for that in former ages, both the greateſt and wiſeſt ſort of people were Practitioners and Students in Aſtrologie;<note place="margin">The great eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie was in in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages.</note> as firſt we may ſee by the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom it was not lawful for any man to take the functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of prieſt-hood on him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he were an Aſtrologer; nor could any be choſen King, except he were of the Colledg, of Prieſts. And <hi>Rodiginus</hi> reporteth that for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169799:19"/>
the prevention of Treaſon, there was none borne within that Kingdom, whoſe Nativity was not brought to the King to be judged on. And <hi>Dion</hi> recordeth the ſame to be practiſed by <hi>Tiberius,</hi> and we ſee in <hi>Daniel,</hi> that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narks of <hi>Babylon</hi> attempted nothing of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without firſt asking Counſel of the <hi>Caldeans.</hi> And the Kings of <hi>Lacedaemonia</hi> had none in their Councels, neither were any ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſit, but who were Aſtrologers: and alſo among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> none was admitted to the Crown, but who were excellently skilled in Aſtrologie; nay even at this day there is no King but hath his Mathematitian about him. So then, it is cleared, that there is no Councel but what is ignorant of Art and Religion, that wil condemn or decree any thing againſt Aſtrologie, and how it hath been eſteemed amongſt the wiſeſt and greateſt of the people. And that ye may be the better confirmed in what hath beene already ſayed; I wil give the names of moſt of the chiefeſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks, Fathers, Kings, Emperours and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, (according as that worthy and Noble Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon</hi> ſets them downe at the latter end of his Book, in defiance of judicial Aſtrologie) that have been ſtudents in this noble Art.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169799:19"/>
                     <head>Aſtronomers and Aſtrologers from the Creation, or our firſt Father ADAM. <hi>Before CHRIST.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <label>1 <hi>ADam.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 3032</item>
                     <label>2 <hi>Seth.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2930</item>
                     <label>3 <hi>Enoch.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2923</item>
                     <label>4 <hi>Kenan.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2625</item>
                     <label>5 <hi>Mahalaleel.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2617</item>
                     <label>6 <hi>Jared.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2520</item>
                     <label>7 <hi>Henoch.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2074</item>
                     <label>8 <hi>Zoroaſter.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2142</item>
                     <label>9 <hi>Methuſelah.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2366</item>
                     <label>10 <hi>Lamech.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2311</item>
                     <label>11 <hi>Noah.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 2155</item>
                     <label>12 <hi>Sem.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1803</item>
                     <label>13 <hi>Arphaxad.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1875</item>
                     <label>14 <hi>Sale.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1835</item>
                     <label>15 <hi>Heber.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1875</item>
                     <label>16 <hi>Peleg. Pheleg.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1966</item>
                     <label>17 <hi>Regu.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1935</item>
                     <label>18 <hi>Sarug.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1922</item>
                     <label>19 <hi>Nachor.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1965</item>
                     <label>20 <hi>Therach.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1878</item>
                     <label>21 <hi>A raham.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1839</item>
                     <label>22 <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1731</item>
                     <label>23 <hi>Jacob.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1706</item>
                     <label>24 <hi>Albion Anglus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1704</item>
                     <label>25 <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <label>26 <hi>Ninus rex aſſyriorum</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1679</item>
                     <label>27 <hi>Prometheus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1802</item>
                     <label>28 <hi>Orion.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1802</item>
                     <label>29 <hi>Atlas.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1792</item>
                     <label>30 <hi>Mercurius Triſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1532</item>
                     <label>31 <hi>Hyas Atlantis filius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1500</item>
                     <label>32 <hi>Aeſculapius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1462</item>
                     <label>Annubis rex Aegypti.</label>
                     <item>Anno 1457</item>
                     <label>34 <hi>Petoſeris.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1420</item>
                     <label>35 <hi>Necepſus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1400</item>
                     <label>36 <hi>Melampus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1357</item>
                     <label>37 <hi>Orpheus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1300</item>
                     <label>38 <hi>Linus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1252</item>
                     <label>39 <hi>Ariſteus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1250</item>
                     <label>40 <hi>Muſaeus Eleuſinus diſcipulus Orphei.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1250</item>
                     <label>41 <hi>Endymion Latmius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1240</item>
                     <label>42 <hi>Phineus Phaenicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1220</item>
                     <label>43 <hi>Chirion.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1202</item>
                     <label>44 <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1185</item>
                     <label>45 <hi>Homerus Chius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1072</item>
                     <label>46 <hi>Phidon Arginus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 812</item>
                     <label>47 <hi>Homerus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 742</item>
                     <label>48 <hi>Heſiodus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 642</item>
                     <label>49 <hi>Epimenides.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 592</item>
                     <label>50 <hi>Thales mileſius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 582</item>
                     <label>51 <hi>Solon.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 580</item>
                     <label>52 <hi>Anaximander mileſius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 572</item>
                     <label>53 <hi>Ariſteus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 552</item>
                     <label>54 <hi>Theognis Megarenſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 544</item>
                     <label>55 <hi>Xenophon.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 542</item>
                     <label>56 <hi>Pythagoras.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 520</item>
                     <label>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169799:20"/>57 <hi>Anaximenes mileſius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 521</item>
                     <label>58 <hi>Democritus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 506</item>
                     <label>59 <hi>Heraclitus Epheſius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 503</item>
                     <label>60 <hi>Zamolxis Seytha, Pythagorae diſcipulus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 490</item>
                     <label>61 <hi>Lucippus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 482</item>
                     <label>62 <hi>Anaxagoras.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 480</item>
                     <label>63 <hi>Empedocles.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 458</item>
                     <label>64 <hi>Democritus Abderita.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 456</item>
                     <label>65 <hi>Empedocles Agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 452</item>
                     <label>66 <hi>Ariſtarchus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 452</item>
                     <label>67 <hi>Archelaus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 450</item>
                     <label>68 <hi>Meliſſus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 442</item>
                     <label>69 <hi>Meton Athenienſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 432</item>
                     <label>70 <hi>Criton.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 432</item>
                     <label>71 <hi>Protagoras.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 430</item>
                     <label>72 <hi>Helicon Cizicenus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 420</item>
                     <label>73 <hi>Euclides Megarenſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 420</item>
                     <label>74 <hi>Theetaetus Athenienſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 412</item>
                     <label>75 <hi>Antiſthenes Athenienſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 412</item>
                     <label>76 <hi>Eudoxus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 398</item>
                     <label>77 <hi>Polymarchus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 398</item>
                     <label>78 <hi>Parmenides Eleates.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 382</item>
                     <label>79 <hi>Dicaearchus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 342</item>
                     <label>80 <hi>Heraclides.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 340</item>
                     <label>81 <hi>Zenocrates.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 330</item>
                     <label>82 <hi>Conon Samius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 330</item>
                     <label>83 <hi>Calippus Cydonius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 330</item>
                     <label>84 <hi>Caliſthenes.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 329</item>
                     <label>85 <hi>Theophraſtus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 320</item>
                     <label>86 <hi>Polemon.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 318</item>
                     <label>87 <hi>Timocharis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 292</item>
                     <label>88 <hi>Euclides.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 292</item>
                     <label>89 <hi>Ariſtillus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 290</item>
                     <label>90 <hi>Aratus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 284</item>
                     <label>91 <hi>Cleoſtratus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 282</item>
                     <label>92 <hi>Ptolomeus Philadel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 280</item>
                     <label>93 <hi>Callimachus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 480</item>
                     <label>94 <hi>Theocritus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 280</item>
                     <label>95 <hi>Bion.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 280</item>
                     <label>96 <hi>Pletades vel ſeptem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poetae.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 270</item>
                     <label>97 <hi>Ariſtarchus ut alii volunt hoc tempore floruit.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 267</item>
                     <label>98 <hi>Dionyſius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 261</item>
                     <label>99 <hi>Eratoſthenes.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 213</item>
                     <label>100 <hi>Archimedes.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 210</item>
                     <label>101 <hi>Sulpitius gallus Conſul Romanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 160</item>
                     <label>102 <hi>Ariſtotherus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 160</item>
                     <label>103 <hi>Colophonius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 140</item>
                     <label>104 <hi>Nicander.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 140</item>
                     <label>105 <hi>Hipparchus Rhodius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 126</item>
                     <label>106 <hi>Publius Nigidus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 58</item>
                     <label>107 <hi>Theodoſius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 56</item>
                     <label>108 <hi>Theagenes.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 50</item>
                     <label>109 <hi>Vitruvius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 50</item>
                     <label>100 <hi>Lucius Tarucius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 50</item>
                     <label>111 <hi>Achoreus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 49</item>
                     <label>112 <hi>C. Julius Caeſar.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 47</item>
                     <label>113 <hi>Soſigenes.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 47</item>
                     <label>114 <hi>Sulla.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 47</item>
                     <label>115 <hi>M. Flavius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 47</item>
                     <label>116 <hi>M. Manilius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 30</item>
                     <label>117 <hi>Maternus Firmicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 5</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:169799:20"/>
                     <head>Aſtronomers and Aſtrologers ſince the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of our Saviour Chriſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon</hi> doth record them.</head>
                     <label>1 <hi>C. Julius Higinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 5</item>
                     <label>2 <hi>Artemedorus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 6</item>
                     <label>3 <hi>Germanius Auguſti filius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 10</item>
                     <label>4 <hi>Thraſillus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 17</item>
                     <label>5 <hi>Gamaliel Chriſti diſcipulus Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus inclitus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 34</item>
                     <label>6 <hi>Columella.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 50</item>
                     <label>7 <hi>Marinus Tyrius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 60</item>
                     <label>8 <hi>Andromachus Cretenſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 67</item>
                     <label>9 <hi>Agrippa Agris in Bithynia.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 90</item>
                     <label>10 <hi>Menelaus Romanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 90</item>
                     <label>11 <hi>Aſcletarion.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 90</item>
                     <label>12 <hi>Proclus Licius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 90</item>
                     <label>13 <hi>Mileus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 96</item>
                     <label>14 <hi>Apollonius Tyraneus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 98</item>
                     <label>15 <hi>Hermippus Beritius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 120</item>
                     <label>16 <hi>Theon Alexandrinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 130</item>
                     <label>17 <hi>Claudius Ptolomeus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 139</item>
                     <label>18 <hi>Ammonius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 135</item>
                     <label>19 <hi>Antigonus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 135</item>
                     <label>20 <hi>Cornelius fronto,</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 150</item>
                     <label>21 <hi>Abidas.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 170</item>
                     <label>22 <hi>Apollinaris.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 170</item>
                     <label>23 <hi>Plotinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 160</item>
                     <label>24 <hi>Amelius Apanteus,</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 270</item>
                     <label>25 <hi>Porphyrius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 280</item>
                     <label>26 <hi>Jamblicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 290</item>
                     <label>27 <hi>Sopater Apameus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 290</item>
                     <label>28 <hi>Dorotheus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 290</item>
                     <label>29 <hi>Julius firmicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 320</item>
                     <label>30 <hi>Syrianus Alexandrinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 320</item>
                     <label>31 <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 320</item>
                     <label>32 <hi>Theon Alexandrinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 360</item>
                     <label>33 <hi>Theon e Muſeo Aegyp.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 380</item>
                     <label>34 <hi>Apollonius Pergeus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 380</item>
                     <label>35 <hi>Pappus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 380</item>
                     <label>36 <hi>Procus Lycius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 390</item>
                     <label>37 <hi>Iſodorus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 391</item>
                     <label>38 <hi>Ammonias.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 400</item>
                     <label>39 <hi>Heliodorus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 400</item>
                     <label>40 <hi>Rufus feſtus Anienus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 410</item>
                     <label>41 <hi>Cleomenes.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 427</item>
                     <label>42 <hi>Cyrillus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 427</item>
                     <label>43 <hi>Poſſidonius Apher.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 470</item>
                     <label>44 <hi>Victorinus Aquitanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 470</item>
                     <label>45 <hi>Phyloponus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 490</item>
                     <label>46 <hi>Dionyſius Abbas Romanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 532</item>
                     <label>47 <hi>Proclus Byzantius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 500</item>
                     <label>48 <hi>Hero Mathematicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 500</item>
                     <label>49 <hi>Olimpiodorus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 500</item>
                     <label>50 <hi>Boetius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 520</item>
                     <label>51 <hi>Marimes Neopolitanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 525</item>
                     <label>52 <hi>Victor Campanes</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 540</item>
                     <label>53 <hi>Artuillus Scotus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 710</item>
                     <label>54 <hi>Adelmus Balduinus Anglus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 710</item>
                     <label>55 <hi>Beda.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 730</item>
                     <label>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169799:21"/>56 <hi>Albumaſer.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 844</item>
                     <label>57 <hi>Albategnius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 879</item>
                     <label>58 <hi>Arzahel Hiſpanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 879</item>
                     <label>59 <hi>Abbo floriacenſis caenobii Abbas.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1004</item>
                     <label>60 <hi>Campanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1030</item>
                     <label>61 <hi>Hermanus Contractus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1040</item>
                     <label>62 <hi>Almeo Arabs.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1048</item>
                     <label>63 <hi>Azophi Arabs.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1061</item>
                     <label>64 <hi>Robertus Lotharin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus Anglus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1091</item>
                     <label>65 <hi>Rodulphus Brughenſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1140</item>
                     <label>66 <hi>Abram Auenezre.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1145</item>
                     <label>67 <hi>Aboali.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1145</item>
                     <label>68 <hi>Jo. Hiſpalenſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1146</item>
                     <label>69 <hi>Thebit.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1195</item>
                     <label>70 <hi>Hali Abanragel.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1202</item>
                     <label>71 <hi>Alkindus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1235</item>
                     <label>72 <hi>Jo. de Sacrobuſto Anglus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1240</item>
                     <label>73 <hi>Alphonſus rex Caſtiliae</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1252</item>
                     <label>74 <hi>Vitellia.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1274</item>
                     <label>75 <hi>Rogerus Bacon Anglus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1280</item>
                     <label>76 <hi>Guido Bonatus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1284</item>
                     <label>77 <hi>Guilielmus de S. Godialdo.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1293</item>
                     <label>78 <hi>Michael Scotus Anglus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1293</item>
                     <label>79 <hi>Jo. de Dacia.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1300</item>
                     <label>80 <hi>Jo. Dank de Saxo ia.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1300</item>
                     <label>81 <hi>Jo. de Ligneriis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1300</item>
                     <label>82 <hi>Rich. Walingforth S. Albani abbas, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1326</item>
                     <label>83 <hi>Jo. Eſtuidi. Anglicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1340</item>
                     <label>84 <hi>Leupoldus de Auſtria.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1340</item>
                     <label>85 <hi>Jo. Eligerus de Gon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doſtenen.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1350</item>
                     <label>86 <hi>Rober. de Leceſtria Anglicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1350</item>
                     <label>87 <hi>Jo de ginunden.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1400</item>
                     <label>88 <hi>Petrus de Aliaco.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1400</item>
                     <label>89 <hi>Henricus de Haffia.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1400</item>
                     <label>90 <hi>Jo Blanchinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1440</item>
                     <label>91 <hi>Georgius Purbachius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1462</item>
                     <label>92 <hi>Nicholaus de Cuſa.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1462</item>
                     <label>93 <hi>Io Iovinianus Pontanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1462</item>
                     <label>94 <hi>Jo. de Monte regio.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1467</item>
                     <label>95 <hi>Eherhardus Schlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinger Tygurinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1470</item>
                     <label>96 <hi>Abraham Zacuti.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1470</item>
                     <label>97 <hi>Georgius Trapezuntius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1480</item>
                     <label>98 <hi>Marſilius Ficinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1490</item>
                     <label>99 <hi>Bernardus Warterus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1490</item>
                     <label>100 <hi>Dominicus Maria Bononienſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1490</item>
                     <label>101 <hi>Jo. Lucilius San tritte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1500</item>
                     <label>102 <hi>Jo. Ganivetus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1500</item>
                     <label>103 <hi>Omer Aſtronomus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1503</item>
                     <label>104 <hi>Jo. Muniz.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1503</item>
                     <label>105 <hi>Lucius Bellantius Senenſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1503</item>
                     <label>106 <hi>Jo. Schreterus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1504</item>
                     <label>107 <hi>Jo. Warnerus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1512</item>
                     <label>108 <hi>Jo. Angelus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1512</item>
                     <label>109 <hi>Jo. Eſizer.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1514</item>
                     <label>110 <hi>Jo Stopherus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1530</item>
                     <label>111 <hi>Jo. Carion.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1530</item>
                     <label>112 <hi>Lucas Gauricus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1530</item>
                     <label>113 <hi>Joachimus Rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelber genſis.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1530</item>
                     <label>114 <hi>Achille P. Gaſſarus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1530</item>
                     <label>115 <hi>Aegidius Tiſchudus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1530</item>
                     <label>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:169799:21"/>116 <hi>Orontius Fineus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1530</item>
                     <label>117 <hi>Andreas Stiborius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1534</item>
                     <label>118 <hi>Jo. Stabius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1534</item>
                     <label>119 <hi>P. Appianus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1534</item>
                     <label>120 <hi>Vitus Minſhemius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1536</item>
                     <label>121 <hi>Albertus Pighius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1536</item>
                     <label>122 <hi>Hieronymus Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtorius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>123 <hi>Jo. Virdungus Halfurtus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>124 <hi>Subaſtiames Man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſterus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>125 <hi>Jo. Dryander.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>126 <hi>Franciſcus Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>127 <hi>Jo. Schonerus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>128 <hi>Georgius Joach Rheticus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>129 <hi>Gualterus Riffe.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>130 <hi>Nicholaus Copernicus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1540</item>
                     <label>131 <hi>Michael Angelus Blondus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1544</item>
                     <label>132 <hi>Nicholaus Sophianus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1458</item>
                     <label>133 <hi>Angerius Ferrerius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1548</item>
                     <label>134 <hi>Caſparus Penſerus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1551</item>
                     <label>135 <hi>Eraſmus Rheinholdus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1551</item>
                     <label>136 <hi>Jo. Roias.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1551</item>
                     <label>137 <hi>Cyprianus Leovicius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1551</item>
                     <label>138 <hi>Jacobus Millichius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1551</item>
                     <label>139 <hi>Michael Noſtradamus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1553</item>
                     <label>140 <hi>Nicholaus Simus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1553</item>
                     <label>141 <hi>Hier. Cardanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1553</item>
                     <label>142 <hi>Genema Friſius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1556</item>
                     <label>143 <hi>Chriſtoph. Stathmio.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1556</item>
                     <label>144 <hi>Chonradus Daſypodius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1556</item>
                     <label>145 <hi>Jo. Stadius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1560</item>
                     <label>146 <hi>Petrus Nonnius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1560</item>
                     <label>147 <hi>Thomas Boderius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1560</item>
                     <label>148 <hi>Samuel Syderocrates.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1560</item>
                     <label>149 <hi>Jo. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1570</item>
                     <label>150 <hi>Joffrancus Officius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1570</item>
                     <label>151 <hi>Valentinus Nabod.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1573</item>
                     <label>152 <hi>Jo. Garcus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1573</item>
                     <label>153 <hi>Gerardus Mercator.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1573</item>
                     <label>154 <hi>Eraſmus Sciec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenfuſſius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1573</item>
                     <label>155 <hi>Nichodem. Friſchrinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1580</item>
                     <label>156 <hi>Cornelius Gemma.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1580</item>
                     <label>157 <hi>Henricus Ranzovius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1582</item>
                     <label>158 <hi>Chiſtoph. Clevius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1582</item>
                     <label>159 <hi>Hier. Wolfius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1582</item>
                     <label>160 <hi>Bartholom. Scultetus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1582</item>
                     <label>161 <hi>Blundevil.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1582</item>
                     <label>162 <hi>Jacob. Chriſtmannus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1582</item>
                     <label>163 <hi>Jo. Henricus Rothmannus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1582</item>
                     <label>164 <hi>Sextus ab Heminga.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1482</item>
                     <label>165 <hi>Franciſcus Iunctinus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1590</item>
                     <label>166 <hi>Gerardus Mercator.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1590</item>
                     <label>167 <hi>Peucerus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1590</item>
                     <label>168 <hi>Bartholomeus Petiſcus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1600</item>
                     <label>169 <hi>Henricus Buntingus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1600</item>
                     <label>170 <hi>Adrianus Romanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1600</item>
                     <label>171 <hi>Origanus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1600</item>
                     <label>172 <hi>Thomas Finxius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1602</item>
                     <label>173 <hi>Enerartus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1602</item>
                     <label>174 <hi>Tycho Brache.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1602</item>
                     <label>175 <hi>Aſlacius.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1602</item>
                     <label>176 <hi>Jo. Maginus.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1602</item>
                     <label>177 <hi>Wright.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1602</item>
                     <label>178 <hi>Meſtlin.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <item>Anno 1602</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:169799:22"/>Theſe are it ſeemes, as many as this good man could hear of, before his time that were remarkeable; yet let us not forget learned <hi>Cornelius Agrippa,</hi> and himſelf. <hi>Blagrave</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Mathematical Jewel, <hi>Hartgil,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent (both for learning and induſtry) <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gol</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and many innumerable others there are, which if I ſhould undertake to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, this whole volume would not be able to containe half of them, beſides thoſe that have privately ſtudied it in all ages, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made their names vulgarly known.</p>
                  <p>And let us not forget thoſe of our times, here in our own Nation, (though we know not thoſe that are in others.) <hi>viz.</hi> Mr <hi>Lilly</hi> who hath put our Aſtrological rules (for the better inſtruction of our Nation) into Engliſh. Doctor <hi>Phiſke,</hi> Mr. <hi>Booker,</hi> Capt. <hi>George Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Vin. Wing,</hi> and many others which for brevity ſake I omit, and haſten to ſhew you the antiquity of the Art, ſince you have already ſeene the lawfulneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, being allowed of by the Scripture, and the wiſeſt and religiouseſt of men.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169799:22"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Demonſtrating the antiquity of Aſtrologie</head>
                  <p>WE have ſeene already how Aſtrologie hath been proved lawful by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and reaſon, not condemned by Councels, but admired and honoured in all ages, by the wiſeſt of the ancients; we come now to ſhew it's Antiquity, and from whence it had it's firſt originall; concerning this point, there hath been much controverſie amongſt Writers, but moſt hold, that it was firſt revealed to man in the infancy of the world by God; <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> deriveth it from the <hi>Egyptians, Tully</hi> from the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> other from the <hi>Sydonians, Calde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Perſians, Indians, Arabians</hi> and <hi>Greeks;</hi> but how ever it is moſt certain, if we will believe the ancienteſt Hiſtoriographers, that the Prieſts and Kings amongſt the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>Caldeans</hi> among the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> the <hi>Magicians</hi> among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Gymnoſophiſts</hi> among the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> the chief Philoſopers of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and the <hi>Druides</hi> of <hi>France</hi> were all Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and eſteemed by thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the wiſeſt men.<note place="margin">The antiquity of Aſtrologie.</note> But <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> in his Antiquities, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. deriveth it from <hi>Adam</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:169799:23"/>
and <hi>Seth:</hi> and that they taught it to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and that <hi>Seth</hi> was ſo wel skilled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that foreſeeing thereby the deſtruction of the world, firſt by Water, then by Fire, leſt the knowledge ſhould periſh by the Flood, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graved it in two Pillers, the one of Stone, the other of Brick; and he farther witneſſeth <hi>that of Stone to remaine in</hi> Syria <hi>in his owne time;</hi> and in the third Chapter of the ſame booke, he affirmeth, that man lived ſo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Flood (by the permiſſion of God) to learn Arts and Sciences, eſpecially naming Aſtrologie and Geometry, the which (ſaith he) <hi>Ediſcere non potuiſſent, niſi ſexcentis viverent annis,</hi> could not be learned under ſix hundred yeares time, for theſe are ſtudyes that require much experience, and particular obſervation, which could not be done on an inſtant. Again in his eight Chapter of the ſame firſt booke of his antiquities, he further affirmeth, that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> having learned this knowledge in <hi>Chaldea</hi> being the place of his birth, when he came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Egypt,</hi> he firſt taught the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> the knowledge of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie and Arithmetick,<note place="margin">How the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> learned Aſtrologie.</note> and ſince the <hi>Egyptians</hi> have been moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite therein, ſo that ſome Hiſtorians have believed <hi>Atlas</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> to be the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venter thereof, others have thought <hi>Henoch</hi> and <hi>Atlas</hi> to be both one, but moſt Hiſtoriographers
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169799:23"/>
hold <hi>Atlas</hi> to be after the Flood. It is vaine longer here to remaine, ſince generally Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie by moſt (eſpecially the moſt judicious) Hiſtoryographers hold it to be derived from God to <hi>Adam,</hi> and that it is the moſt ancient of all Arts and Sciences, except Arithmetick; wherefore leſt this diſcourſe ſwel to a bigger bulk then I would willingly have it, I haſten to the fourth and laſt leſſon I promiſed to ſhew Mr. <hi>Homes,</hi> and that is to ſhew him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> That Aſtrologie is the moſt profitableſt ſtudy reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the ſun to mortals.</head>
                  <p>WHich I ſhal indeavour to make cleare thus; firſt, That it is moſt profitable for the knowledge of <hi>morall Philoſophie, viz.</hi> of our ſelves and others. Secondly, For <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Philoſophie.</hi> Thirdly, For <hi>Phyſicke.</hi> Fourthly, For <hi>Health.</hi> Fifthly, For <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry.</hi> Sixthly, For giving a reaſon for <hi>Climacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall</hi> yeares (which other Arts cannot) and other things. Seventhly, and laſtly, For <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Diſcipline.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Aſtrologie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophy.</note> that it is moſt profitable for the knowledge of moral Philoſophy, Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> will not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169799:24"/>
deny (if he know any thing in the Art,) that the conſtitution of the body, and the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the minde is by Aſtrologie known; ſo that hereby we receive a double benefit, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, admonition to refraine what may prove obnoxious and hurtful to our health. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, incouragement to apply our ſelves to that whereunto we are born apt by nature, beſides we may alſo be warned hereby, of what may cauſe the minde by ill government to offend others. And for felicity the chief end of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophy; no Art or Science can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with Aſtrologie, for it teacheth a man what pertaines to the goods of the body and minde, and ſo alſo to moderate the unruly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, whoſe violence carrieth away the minde from that golden meane wherein vertue dwels and keeps her place; ſo likewiſe in the external goods, it reſolveth a man what hopes or likelihood by his own induſtry, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies he hath to attaine to the riches of this world; and alſo teacheth him how to increaſe the ſame, by what meanes, at what time, and in what place it wil be beſt for him, or moſt profitable to this intent or purpoſe. So that then ye ſee Aſtrologie to comprehend more in one part, then all the Arts in the world put together, in any or all parts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">For naturall Philoſophy.</note>Secondly, For natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, it bringeth no leſſe helpe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169799:24"/>
then to the former, for hereby the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher commeth to know God the upholder and immoveable Creator of all things, by the conſtant inchangeable motion of the heavens; and the corruption and generation of all things, by the motion of ☉, <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> and other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in the Zodiack; and that there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain prefixt time of every ones life that is born, allotted by the Stars, and that this is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers according to the nature of every conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and the meaſure of every proper revolution; as alſo the reaſon of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea, by the motion of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. He comes alſo by Aſtrologie to know the riſings of Meteors, the motion of Comets, and innumerable other things, much condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the furtherance of his knowledge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and skil. But this is ſo clear, I haſten to what is further to be ſaid in the praiſe and utility of Aſtrologie, leſt I ſpend too much time in confuting ſuch weak ſtuffe, as is this diſcourſe of Mr. <hi>Homes,</hi> againſt ſo apparent a Noble and excellent Art.</p>
                  <p>Thirdy, For Phyſick, for all that knows any thing in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, can acquaint Mr. <hi>Homes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aſtrologie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</note> as alſo his great friend <hi>Gallen</hi> (as moſt falſely he accuſes him (in his 115. page) to condemn Aſtrology as Sophiſtical, when indeed he himſelf appeares no other at
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169799:25"/>
the beſt, to wrong ſo worthy a man.) That he that ſhal adminiſter Phyſick when the Sunne comes to the equinoctial points, or in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicular or Dog-dayes and the like, knowes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little either in the one or other, <hi>viz.</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick or Aſtrologie; and is rather to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a foole then a Phyſitian; and further, <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> admoniſheth men not to truſt themſelves with that Phyſitian that is not verſed in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie; and <hi>Hippocrates</hi> alſo ſayeth, that that Phyſitian which is ignorant in Aſtrologie, is not fully, nor can he be perfectly known in his Art; for without Aſtrologie, he ſhal never be able to give Phyſick ſafely, <hi>viz.</hi> when to purge by evacuation or vomit, or Phlebotomie, or for what humours, or in what quantity, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he know or come to the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the chief Piller of his Art, <hi>viz.</hi> The true cauſe of the Malady without it, neither with it, (if wel learned therein) can he erre, beſides <hi>Gallen</hi> further affirmeth, that Phyſick given at unſeaſonable times, doth not onely little availe or helpe, but often times prove very hurtful, even to the indangering of the life of the Patient; and that theſe times are onely to be known and judged by the Starres. <hi>Fernelius</hi> (a learned Phyſitian) doth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto alſo condeſcend, as alſo <hi>Ficinus;</hi> for there is nothing more certain, then that Aſtrologie doth plainly deliver rules for all the parts of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169799:25"/>
Phyſick aboveſaid, (which Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> I am confident (if any whit read therein) dare not but confeſſe) and not onely ſo, but teacheth alſo the critial dayes, without which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be known with any certainty; wherefore it is, that thoſe Phyſitians ignorant in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, conclude the ſeventh and fourteenth dayes to be dangerous, when moſt times they are deceived, and ſo conſequently apply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary remedies to their Patients, much to their prejudice,<note place="margin">The reaſon of Critical dayes.</note> if not abſolute deſtruction: The reaſon is, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> by her various motion commeth ſometimes ſooner, and ſometimes latter, to her <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> and ☍ or quadrat and oppoſit part of the place ſhe was in at the beginning of the diſeaſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Sometimes ſhe comes to her <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> in ſeven dayes, ſometimes not till the eight or ninth day, other times at the ſixth dayes; and to her ☍ ſometimes at the fourteenth day, ſometimes at the thirteen day, other times not till the ſixteenth day. I would faine now Mr. <hi>Homes,</hi> you would ſhew what Art in the whole earth, is more beneficial to Phyſick, then A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, &amp;c. but I haſten to the remaining proofs.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, For health,<note place="margin">Aſtrologie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for health.</note> which none but the moſt ignorant and malicious wil deny, ſince the conſtitution of the body the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169799:26"/>
ground, wiſe Phyſitians go upon and look firſt too; that, that foundation being layd, they may then fall to the rebuilding of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, otherwiſe (as you have heard) deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (like a houſe founded on the ſand) is to be expected. Then conſequently the moſt envious cannot but confeſſe and acknowledge it to be the moſt profitable thing for our health under the Sun. Wherefore then let us ſee whether the husband-man will acknowledge it to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to him in his way of living, <hi>viz.</hi> Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Aſtrologie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry.</note>Fifthly, Husbandry, and firſt let me aske him, whether he lops his Trees from the time the Sun declines from our Horizon, till he againe reenters the equinoctial point? or if he knows not (if he ſhould) that it wil not grow again? or whether he uſe to ſow Peaſe in the increaſe of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>? or if ſo, whether they wil then ever leave blooming or bloſſoming? or whether therefore he doth not obſerve and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to ſet them in the waine, or decreaſe of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. Nay, it is reported of the women in the North, both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they diligently obſerve a time of the Moon to ſet their Egges, that they may all come to good; and furthermore, let me aske the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man, whether he obſerveth not a time to graffe, and prune his Trees? but this is ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169799:26"/>
common, that to ſpend more time hereunto, were to no purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly,<note place="margin">For rendrin a reaſon for Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macterical years</note> For rendring a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for Climacterical yeares, it happening by the profection of the Planets and Horoſcope, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant or firſt Houſe (as ye may call it) to the ☍ or <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> aſpects or their places in Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or by the motion of ♄ if he have any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Nativity, for <hi>Ptolomie</hi> and the wiſeſt in this Art, give ♄ as much power in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree ſeveral of yeares, as the Sunne hath in months, or the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in dayes; and if his courſe be obſerved, it will bee found finiſhed much about the ſame number of years, as the Moones is in dayes; and further, that ♄ in every ſeven years comes either to <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ of his place in the Radix of Nativities. And further know, that if there be no danger (as we find by experience) of ſome mens lives, at theſe yeares, they have either ſome of the beneficial Planets in their eight Houſe, or the direction of the aſcendant,<note place="margin">Looke <hi>Ranzo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</note> or Aphetical places are free from all impediment and affliction, of the interficient and malignant conſtellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>Seventhly, and laſtly,<note place="margin">Aſtrologie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary affaires.</note> for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Diſcipline, Hiſtory is full of examples herein, and for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169799:27"/>
ſake (becauſe I will haſten to conclude this firſt Chapter, that I may proceed to Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his ſecond Section) I will hear content my ſelf with this one, which the Indian Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhew forth unto us; which is, that <hi>Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> having the Art of Aſtrologie, and being in a ſtraight for want of Victual, together with the whole Army of the King of <hi>Spaine Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand;</hi> and foreſeeing an Eclipſe of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in few daies to happen; threatned the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans he would ſend infinite plagues amongſt them, if they ſpeedily relieved them not; in token whereof, they ſhould at ſuch a time ſee the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> light taken from them, which they at firſt ſlighted, but when they ſaw according to the former words, that the Moon began to be darkened, and grew ſo more and more, and being ignorant of the cauſe thereof, did not onely ſend them the victual they former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly retained from them, but alſo threw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at <hi>Columbus</hi> feet, asking forgiveneſſe: So then you have had (as brief as may be) ſhewn unto you, <hi>what Aſtrologie is, that it is an Art, and a lawfull Art, allowed of by Scripture; the antiquity of it, and the utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it;</hi> there is it may be ſome Arts, that may be beneficial or helpful to another; but you ſee both poſitively and concluſively, that Aſtrologie is generally helpful to all Arts and Sciences, nay what other ſtudy in the whole
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169799:27"/>
world in this point is like it or able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with it? and ſeeing it is ſo, very indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly and unfitly, doth Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> joyn it or compare it with <hi>Augury, Auruſpicie, Auſpicie, Pullarie, Necromancy, Sortelegie, Onieroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> or <hi>Palmeſtry,</hi> which are no Arts, as he clearly ſeeth this is; and that by the judgement of the wiſeſt men and greateſt Philoſophers; wherefore if he will be wiſer then all theſe he hath been ſhewn, by my conſent, he ſhall be elected the 8th wiſe man; wherefore ſeeing truth and authority of theſe, as well as Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, ſtandeth with it, and diſtinguiſheth it from theſe ſortelegies, haphazards and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; it mattereth not what either he doth or can ſay, or do, againſt it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> In Anſwer to the opinions of the learned touching Astrologie; wherein is further ſhewn, the lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Aſtrologie; that the Stars are both ſigns and cauſes; and that <hi>Mr Homes</hi> his quoting the Fathers and learned, is meerly fallacious, and envious, and no wiſe available to his intent and purpoſe.</head>
               <p>I Am come now to Mr <hi>Homes</hi> his ſecond Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherin we ſhal ſee how he vents his malice
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169799:28"/>
moſt invectively all along againſt Aſtrologie; thinking he bringeth the learned to condemn it, but what are the learned Schoolmen, or great Philoſophers to me, or their ſayings in this matter,<note place="margin">Truth and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone whereby all controverſies are decided.</note> further then they have truth and reaſon on their ſide? If they follow their own opinions and conceits without ſound reaſon and warrant, I ſee no warrant or reaſon why I ſhould regard ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them, their words or their quoters.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Wherein is further ſhewn, the legality of Aſtrologie.</head>
                  <p>HIs firſt learned man (then) he begins with, is <hi>Toſtatus,</hi> who he ſaith in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary on <hi>Levit,</hi> 19. Queſt. 28, 29, &amp;c. hath theſe words, the which <hi>Doctor Willet gives him,</hi> viz. <hi>Of things which are (as to us) accidental, as the ſucceſſe of buſineſſe, or their cauſes internal, as mens will and free choice, as to undertake a journey, or to build, or not build, predictions are not onely uncertain, but ſuperſtitious: and the ſame is to be ſaid of caſting of Nativities by the conjunction of the Planets;</hi> but if he had conſidered what reaſon or ground <hi>Toſtatus</hi> hath for theſe words, he had never thus laid them open; and I much
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169799:28"/>
wonder he being a <hi>Divine,</hi> he had not firſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf conſidered and weighed the text, which that he may now do <hi>(Nunquam ſera eſt ad bonos mores via)</hi> I will here ſet it down: <hi>Regard not them that have familiar ſpirits, neither ſeeke after Wizards, to be defiled by them; I am the Lord your God,</hi> Levit. 19.31. where we clearly ſee there is no part of the text, once in the leaſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth or meaneth <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> it is againſt the ſeeking after thoſe that have familiar Spirits, and Wizards;<note place="margin">Looke what A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie is, <hi>pag. 2.</hi>
                     </note> now that Aſtrologie doth not in the leaſt ſavour hereof, is clear in what hath been already ſaid, and the definition thereof, ſee <hi>Ptolomies</hi> own words at the beginning of my diſcourſe in the ſecond page: So that except the reſt of his learned men (as he calleth them) can bring better proof or reaſon then this firſt, he had better have been ſilent, then thus to be overſhot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Wherein is ſhewn that the Stars are ſignes and Cauſes.</head>
                  <p>HE then brings Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> (to caſt his ſquib alſo at this ſtrong Tower, <hi>viz. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie</hi>) in theſe words, <hi>all manner of conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169799:29"/>
(which ſaith he is meant by Aſtrologie) is not unlawful, whereof any Natural or Divine cauſe can be yielded, as firſt there be Natural ſigns in the heavens and ayre, as of the alteration of weather, of winds, of raine, &amp;c.</hi> This doth no whit hurt it, and is onely a flaſh that at the moſt doth but whiz about it, and at the laſt after a great crack, vaniſheth in ſmoke: mark but the words, <hi>all manner of conjecturing is not unlawful, &amp;c.</hi> and ſaith Mr <hi>Homes, ſee he calleth it</hi> (meaning Aſtrologie) <hi>but conjecturing onely;</hi> but doth Mr <hi>Homes</hi> conjecture it to be no other? if he do, it is his ignorance; I hope the reader ſees by this time what Aſtrologie is and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be as much in love with it againe, as ever before by him diſcouraged, as alſo out of love with his cavils; but this is not all, when you ſee him ſtript of his Scripture proofs, you will tell me ſomething then; when you ſee him as naked left, as my naile, of all his <hi>ſophiſtications,</hi> you will tell me then you are worſe in love with him, (I'm confident) when his ugly malice is diſcovered againſt this moſt apparent truth: But let me not forget my ſelf, and ſpend too much time about him, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the diſcourſe in hand; which is, that ſince there hath been already ſhewn, that the Stars have the applauſe of power on the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things of this world, as alſo the great <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomie</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:169799:29"/>
(whoſe word in this caſe I believe wil be taken before Doctor <hi>Willets,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his) gives his word for it;<note place="margin">Aſtrologie no way unlawfull.</note> beſides ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience alſo, as above ſhewed, (and you know <hi>experientia docet</hi>) there is no more to be ſaid, but that Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie is not (as Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> ſayeth) unlawful; neither doth he in any wiſe condemne it, for in his following words he tels us, <hi>There are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſignes in the heavens and aire which cauſe raine, winde, &amp;c.</hi> The cauſe of which, is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the influence of the Stars, which if he deny, all Writers on this Art are contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as alſo the Scripture to boot, if then this be not a ſtrong Argument, let himſelf judge.</p>
                  <p>But to clear this point more fully, what ſayeth Mr. <hi>Homes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nota. As anon ſhall appeare.</note> is the cauſe of Raine, alteration of Aire, and the like? if his Maſter Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> did not in theſe words ſhew it, me thinks he ſhould not have left the Reader unſatisfied; and not onely ſo, but have proved the Stars to have no Influence thereon, nor to be cauſes of theſe alterations, and then his argument had been good; but certainly he that wil carpe at ſuch trivial words as theſe, would not have omitted that, could he but ſufficiently have proved it, which ſince he could not, or did not; he muſt give me leave to prove
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169799:30"/>
they are.<note place="margin">The Stars ſignes and cauſes.</note> And firſt let me give you <hi>Moſes</hi> judgement herein, who plainly tells us, <hi>The Stars are for ſignes and ſeaſons, Gen.</hi> 1.14. which Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> will ſay is fullfilled in the words following, <hi>viz. And God made two great lights, the one to rule, the Day, and the other to rule the Night Gen.</hi> 1.16. To which then I anſwer, by way of Quere, to what end then are theſe invincible, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtable and innumerable hoſtes of Heaven? were they made for no other uſe then to gaze on? the ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> will ſufficiently ſerve our turne for matter of light, if we looke no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into their uſes; but the Scripture further putteth this matter quite out of doubt if we will beleeve Gods own word, <hi>Joh</hi> 28.31. For he ſpeaking of his Omnipotent power, asketh his ſervant <hi>Job,</hi> whether he, or any one elſe <hi>Can reſtraine the influence of the Pleiades, or looſe the bands of Orion:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Saint</hi> Auſtine <hi>on</hi> Job.</note> On which words St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> referreth all men to the ſtudy of Aſtrologie, for the underſtanding of that place; and not onely ſo, but ſhews us that under theſe two conſtellations, the Lord doth comprehend the influence of all the Celeſtial hoſt, figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſing <hi>pars pro toto;</hi> and to ſhew you by experience the verity hereof, if you wil nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beleeve <hi>Auguſtine, Moſes,</hi> nor <hi>God himſelf,</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:169799:30"/>
except you ſee and feele; (not to inſiſt long on this point, which is cleared by ſuch ſtrong and invincible witneſſes; one whereof is able to be ſufficient teſtimony againſt all Mr. <hi>Homes his learned Judges and condemners of Aſtrologie</hi>) For confirming and clearing hereof, then I might here again inſtance that palpable expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience we have of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea, by the influence of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> (as above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) but to manifeſt it yet further, let him call to mind the increaſe and decreaſe of ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, the mutation and variation of times, and innumerable other effects of the Stars, which (if time and conveniency would permit) might be recorded, and let him then ſtudy the cauſe hereof, and he will then without doubt be of an other tenent; let him obſerve alſo when ♄ and ☉ is in <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, or when ♂ and ♀ is in <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ or ♃ and ☿ are ſo poſited, and let him tell me then, what alterations they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in the aire both by Raine, Snow, Wind, Tempeſts, Thundering and Lightning, and the like according to their ſeveral poſitions, the nature of ſignes and houſes and manſions they are in; (which if he be not altogether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Art, he may dayly ſee) theſe and the like effects, are moſt vulgarly known by experience, ſo that therefore he might even as well have confeſſed thoſe ſignes he ſpeaketh of, to be the Stars, and cauſes their influence, ſince
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169799:31"/>
he doth not, nor cannot ſhew me any other thing they are, without wronging and ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Art; and contradicting the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therein, as alſo the Fathers, St. <hi>Auſtine, Moſes,</hi> nay and GOD himſelf; and if this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not then to all the judicious, an apparant Doctrin of Devils;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> proved rather to be a teacher of the Doctrine of Devils, then Aſtrologers.</note> let the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of capacities judge, but who could indeed looke for better ſtuff in ſo vile a meane ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe; or that beaſt not to be a monſter, or at leaſt to be ſhun'd as very obnoxious, that hath HELL written in it's fore-head? for the title of his <hi>Bell and Dragon,</hi> (which he hopeth ſhal devour Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, with other frivolous and indeed unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Arts, like an unconſcionable judge, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the good with the bad) is DEMO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOLOGIE, OR THE DOCTRIN OR LANGUAGE OF DEVILS; I ſay, is not this moſt wickedly, or elſe moſt ignorantly done of Mr. <hi>Homes,</hi> to deny theſe effects and operations of the Starres above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed, to proceed from the Stars? and ſeeing it is ſo, of neceſſity then muſt Mr. <hi>Homes's</hi> Clerks in this point faile, who have ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably the word of God againſt them; he might as wel then have left out that other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Doctor <hi>Willets;</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>that the Stars have not the ſame influence in ſummer, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169799:31"/>
in Winter, Spring and Autumne, and ſo conſequently will conclude them. Firſt, not to be ſignes</hi> (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the word of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.14. as aboveſaid.) Secondly, <hi>Nor cauſes, quia ex unitate cauſae ſequeretur ſimilitudo effectus, of the ſame cauſe there ſhould follow the ſame effect; but there followeth not the ſame effect from the ſame ſignes, appeares by experience.</hi> As much to ſay, the Stars are neither causes nor ſignes, becauſe they produce not fruits in Winter, as wel as in Summer, or becauſe they cauſe not Snow in Summer, or Buds and Bloſſoms in Winter. O rare cavil! but ſince he is already, by what is aboveſaid, confuted; I ſhal here add nothing but this, that ſince the queſtion is, whether they are cauſes and ſignes, becauſe that paſſage in the firſt of <hi>Gen.</hi> manifeſts they are ſignes, I wil (if he wil be convinced by the word of God) here give him to know they are alſo cauſes, <hi>I will heare the heavens, and the heavens ſhall heare the earth, and the earth the corne and the wine, &amp;c. Hoſ.</hi> 2.2. And in another place, the increaſe of the earth is referred to the <hi>Influence of the Sun and the Moon, Deut.</hi> 33.14. By all which we may clearly ſee (unleſſe blinded with malice and wilfulneſſe) that they are both ſignes and cauſes, of all our earthly injoyments and happineſſes; <hi>Et ſi ſcriptura, &amp; ipſe deus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum, quis contra nos.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:169799:32"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Wherein his allegations againſt the ground of the Art is condemned; and his bringing <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> against it, proved fallacious, injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and malicious; and how far we ought to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the power of the Stars.</head>
                  <p>SEeing then it is moſt clearly ſo, that the Starres are ſignes and cauſes as above ſaid, what need theſe envious carpers or malicious gainſayers of the truth be heeded or regarded; but let their perverſe rags of paper periſh with themſelves, not worthy the leaſt remembrance; and indeed had it not been rightly to inform the vulgar, and to make them ſee, that high language ſerveth not to condemn truth, I had buried both them and their filthy rags in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual oblivion, but I hope ſince they muſt be remembred, it will be but for their diſgrace, not Chronicled for their worthineſſe, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual infamy.</p>
                  <p>But this is not all, he comes next to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Aſtrologie by <hi>Keckerman,</hi> and that with as weak arguments as he did the reſt, <hi>Kecker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a moſt learned Philoſopher, and Chriſtian, although he favours ſome things which men now a daies call part of Aſtrologie, did not in all his two great Volumnes in fol. of Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169799:32"/>
ſet forth any Aſtrologie;</hi> a wiſe ſtory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, becauſe <hi>Keckerman</hi> writeth not of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> therefore there is no ſuch thing, but if <hi>Keckerman</hi> hath not, yet as wiſe and as learned and greater Philoſophers have,<note place="margin">Looke the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter of this Treatiſe, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                     </note> as if the being of Aſtrologie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on his writing hereof, or a whit farther from being an heavenly Science and a lawful Art, becauſe he omitteth it, fine Logick and rare reaſon, if rightly underſtood, and the depth thereof throughly ſearched! becauſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> knew not the reaſon of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea, therefore no body elſe doth, neither is there ſuch a thing in Nature; and becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> writeth not of the creation of Angels, <hi>Ergo,</hi> there is none, O profound and invincible reaſon? but it ſavoureth ſo little of reaſon, that it is rather rime-Dogril, Brains and Staires, or hot and block, I had almoſt ſaid head, that I might make (at leaſt) ſence thereof, if neither rime nor reaſon. But to proceed, (he ſaith) he is ſure he hath theſe words againſt it, <hi>Manent tamen, &amp;c. the Stars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, as of other ſublunary effects, ſo of effects in man, the common and remote cauſe which many wayes may be hindered, not only by the firſt cauſe, God, but alſo by particular cauſes, partly in the Heavens, partly in the Ayre and other Elements; ſo that the Predictions of Aſtrologers are with ifs
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169799:33"/>
and ands, &amp;c.</hi> which is as much to the purpoſe as comes juſt to nothing; for firſt, that God can alter the courſe of the Stars there is no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologer but will confeſſe (but whether he will or no, or ordinarily uſes ſo to do, is the queſtion) ſo that Mr <hi>Homes</hi> gets little by this querk ſince he affirmeth nothing that any Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger will deny: But if Mr <hi>Keckerman</hi> maketh it not appear what particular cauſes hinder the effects of the Stars, me thinks for the ſtrength of his argument Mr <hi>Homes</hi> ſhould have done it; for it ſtandeth not with any reaſon, that ſubordinate cauſes as are the Ayre and other Elements, ſhould predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate or rule over the firſt moving cauſes, <hi>viz.</hi> the Stars; this the weakeſt capacity that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the Art will affirme, and you have but now heard that the effects of the Stars cauſe alteration and mutation of the Ayre, as we alſo daily ſee by experience; and therefore his aſſertion, that the principles of Aſtrologie are not confirmed on true principles, is here alſo condemned as erronious, falſe and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious;<note place="margin">Careleſneſſe in Aſtrologers cauſe errour.</note> for we ſee Aſtrologers ſeldome faile in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, except when they ſwerve from the rules of Art, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Alſteds</hi> aſſertion alſo is here no leſſe ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then the reſt, who ſaith, <hi>Aſtrologers are alſo often deceived,</hi> and what then, becauſe a man
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169799:33"/>
that never was at <hi>London,</hi> miſſeth his way, once or twice, ſhall he conclude there is no ſuch place; ſure it ſhould rather teach him to obſerve diligently his roade, and not turn on the right hand nor the left, and if the Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers would as warily obſerve their rules, this objection of the ignorant had never been thought on. But Mr <hi>Homes,</hi> is Divinity falſe and no wiſe to be heeded; becauſe there is ſo many errours and ſchiſmes crept into the Church? or becauſe every one attaineth not to a full perfection of the Spirit? or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>humanum eſt errare,</hi> man is fraile and ſubject to failings? no ſure, experience, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and truth teacheth us to the contrary: Wherefore he might very well have omitted theſe ſlender reaſons, as alſo that place of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>ſophiſticum eſt, it is ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical,</hi> but how? not as having no verity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but in the ſuperſtitious abuſe thereof, for you ſee clearly in the <hi>firſt Chapter of his Treatiſe,</hi> Galen <hi>holdeth that man a fool, rather then a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, that is not an Aſtrologer:</hi> and in all his works hath Aſtrologie in great eſteeme and applauſe, and moreover teſtifieth his own pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice hereof, eſpecially, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de diebus decret. chap</hi> 2, 3, 4, 5, &amp; 6. and the like: So he brings St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to condemn it, thus in theſe words in his Treatiſe <hi>De Doctrina Chriſtiana,</hi> lib. 2. chap. 21, 22. <hi>eſt magnus error, &amp; magna demen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169799:34"/>
ſuperſtitio: Aſtrologie is a great error mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſuperſtition,</hi> it is clear that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> here ſpeaketh of the ſuperſtitious uſe thereof, as in attributing fatal neceſſity thereto, and in too much truſting and confiding therein, as may appear by what you have already heard St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of it; but to clear it more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, St. <hi>Austin</hi> confeſſeth that before his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, he followed the hereſies of the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees,</hi> who maintained the Stars to be adored and prayed unto,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> chap. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>20.</hi> ch. <hi>6.</hi> contra Fauſtum Manichaeum.</note> and therefore to reclaime the multitude, which went thus a whoring after the waies of the Heathen, this good man uſeth theſe words to recall them, and unite them to the belief of God: But I hope Mr <hi>Homes</hi> will not ſay that <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> are thus ſuperſtitious and wicked; he that ſaith Aſtrologie (as I ſaid before) is any other thing then what is delivered by <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomy,</hi> in the ſecond page of this Treatiſe, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not what Aſtrologie is; Neither will he affirme I hope, that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> condemns <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> but the ſuperſtitious abuſe thereof, which is clear, for he delivereth five opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning deſtiny.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that by deſtiny is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood <hi>the providence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> chap. <hi>1.</hi> De civitate Dei.</note> 
                     <hi>will and power of God,</hi> and therefore he warneth the Aſtrologers, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169799:34"/>
they continue their opinions, but correct their tongues, for through cuſtome of ſpeech the vulgar commonly underſtood nothing by the word <hi>fate</hi> or <hi>deſtiny,</hi> but the inevitable power of the Stars.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is quite contrary to the former, <hi>aſcribing all to the abſolute power of the Stars, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the will of God:</hi> But this opinion derogating from the omnipotent power of God, and his providence in all our actions, he ſaith ought to be rejected, not onely by thoſe that profeſſe the true Religion, but which ſerve or worſhip any gods at all, though never ſo falſe.</p>
                  <p>The third, <hi>ſo attributeth to the decrees of the Stars, that yet they believe them to have this power in ſuch ſort derived unto them from God, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they can, and do determine of us and our actions, as they will themſelves:</hi> which opinion he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth is very wrongfully held of heaven, to maintaine ſuch wickedneſſe to be, as it were inacted in that moſt ſhining Senate, that were the like acted in any Court or State on earth, were worthy to be ſubverted.</p>
                  <p>The fourth opinion is, <hi>that the Stars have neither power nor will to operate on us at their own pleaſures, but as they do neceſſarily execute that which God impoſeth upon them;</hi> which St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> accounteth more intolerable then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that it teacheth us to conceive that of God, which they hold unworthy to impute
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169799:35"/>
unto the Stars,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Gen. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </note> againſt ſuch he ſufficiently declareth.</p>
                  <p>Theſe opinions, St. <hi>Augustine</hi> renounceth, as they rather utterly deny the power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, or, as they impute abſolute rule and dominion of the Stars immediately over the will of man, neceſſarily inforcing us in all our actions; or as they throw all our ſins upon God, whileſt they make him by the Stars inevitably to inforce us to evil: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had Mr <hi>Homes</hi> (as it had beſit a learned man) firſt examined his Authors with good obſervation and deliberation, and not ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily taken hold on every thing he finds delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by others, that he imagineth will ſerve for his turne; I'm confident, he had not thus inconſiderately alleadged St <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> for (as I defined before in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond page, what <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is) ſo the ſame <hi>Ptolomy</hi> confeſſeth <hi>the Stars not to have any fatali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as working by or with a fatal neceſſity on the will or ſoul of man, as much as</hi> St. <hi>Auſtine himſelf;</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them no farther operation in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters then the moſt orthodox and learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines do.</p>
                  <p>The fifth opinion is, <hi>which neither eſteemeth the Stars of their own wils,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">How farre we ought to attribute to the power of the Stars.</note> 
                     <hi>(as if they were living ſouls) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree future events, nor neceſſarily to uſurpe power over our minds, but onely to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169799:35"/>
the inclinations of the elements, and of all things compounded of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now that St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> meant not ſuch Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers as deny <hi>neceſſity</hi> (as Mr <hi>Homes</hi> would faine perſwade the vulgar to believe;) but onely aſcribe power unto the Stars to worke upon ſublunary bodies; is evident by his words, <hi>Non uſque qua<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> abſurde dici poſſit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 5. cap. 6. De civitate Dei.</note> 
                     <hi>ad ſolas corporum diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentias, afflatus quoſdam valere ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereos, ſicut in ſolaribùs acceſſibus, &amp; receſſibus, videmus etiam ipſius anni temporae va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riari &amp; lunaribus incrementis, &amp; decrementis angeri &amp; minui quaedam genera rerum; ſicut Echinos, &amp; conchas, &amp; mirabiles aeſtus oceani, non autem, &amp; animi voluntates poſitionibus ſyderum ſubdi:</hi> where we ſee nothing exempted from ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Stars that is bodily, but onely our ſpirituall part:<note place="margin">St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> concurreth with Aſtrologers. <hi>lib. 2. cap. 5.</hi> De Gen.</note> And he aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth not this power to the Stars in generall, as that their ſpecifical vertues are not poſſible to be known to man, for he concurreth with Aſtrologers, that the quality of ♄ is cold, &amp;c. as you may farther ſee at the beginning of this Chapter. So that you may ſee how falſely and injuriouſly he brings in St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> by which (I will onely add this) the Reader may clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee the envy and malice of Mr. <hi>Homes,</hi> how
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169799:36"/>
he ſtudieth (by the learned and Fathers) to perſwade his reader againſt this moſt apparent truth, <hi>viz.</hi> ASTROLOGIE.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT IV.</hi> Wherein Aſtrologie is defended againſt his allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, from <hi>Mr. Perkins</hi> his words.</head>
                  <p>MAſter <hi>Homes</hi> comes then to tell us Mr <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> a learned man and famous, writ a Treatiſe againſt it, ſo did <hi>Melancthon,</hi> a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſcholler then he, and as knowing a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, write as much and more for it, then he ever did againſt it; what if I ſhould tell him of ſome that have writ againſt the Scripture, is the Word of God therefore falſe and to be rejected? he ſaith Mr <hi>Perkins</hi> cals it <hi>prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>idolatry;</hi> but let the Reader ſeriouſly and diligently but obſerve what hath been here already ſaid, and he cannot but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Mr <hi>Perkins</hi> ſpake onely againſt the abuſe of the Art, not as it is in its ſelf; againſt the ſuperſtitious confidence and truſt in the Stars, not the ſearching and ſtudying of the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and effects of the Stars on elementary bodies; and as much as this comes to, all that ſtudy the Art will confeſſe, <hi>Ergo,</hi> Mr <hi>Homes</hi> is miſtaken to thinke by theſe words of Mr <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:169799:36"/>
to condemn <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> ſince he ſaith no more then all <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> themſelves will ſay; wherefore to dwell longer here, were but vain and <hi>ſuperfluous;</hi> and to as little purpoſe as to bring a man a bag-pudding when he hath fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his belly with pie. We come therefore now to his eighth learned man which condemnes <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> which he tels us is Mr <hi>Geree,</hi> who hath (ſaith he) written a Treatiſe againſt <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> I could if need were, cite as many, and more that have written againſt the Divine word of God, then he can make appear hath written againſt <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> ſhall any man be therefore ſo impudently wicked to conclude the word of God is not true, or not to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, no ſure, this were altogether as impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently wicked as Mr <hi>Homes</hi> his ſequel or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is ridiculous, ſophiſtical and envious. Mr <hi>Chamber</hi> alſo writ a booke againſt <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> which I wonder he remembred not alſo, but that learned Sir <hi>Christopher Heydon</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſuch a repulſe, as that none of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſts or ill willers to the Art, ever durſt undertake to give a reply thereunto; for he doth not onely refute Mr <hi>Chamber,</hi> but alſo <hi>Picus mirandula, Melton, Perkins,</hi> and <hi>Geree</hi> to boote; wherefore I refer all thoſe that would be further reſolved herein, and deſire to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne between truth and falſhood, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of the diſcourſe it ſelf, it being a piece
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169799:37"/>
of that exquiſite wit and learning, that none can be able to ſurpaſſe it, if (in the whole world) be worthy to compare with it; it was never as yet undertaken to be anſwered, neither I beleeve wil it ever be attempted by any of theſe cavilling punies, that gain-ſay indeed what they know not, but by tradition or Theorically, and if practically, it is ſo ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly known by them, that they imagine the Art to be no better then meere Conjuration, and the Artiſts Conjurers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Wherein his cavilling Mr. <hi>Briggs,</hi> and others, are convinced.</head>
                  <p>WE now come (not to be too tedious) to heare what he can tel us of learned Mr. <hi>Briggs,</hi> againſt Aſtrologie, which is brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus much, <hi>That after an earneſt deſire to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the perfection thereof, he ſeriouſly applyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe unto the ſtudy, but in concluſion, when he thought to have had joy of his weried labours, he was ſatisfied with nothing but uncertainty, and meeting an other Astrologer, told him how he had beene deceived in the rules of the Art, (who for his comfort) concluded alſo as he did, that there was no certainty therein, upon which he left off further
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169799:37"/>
studying thereof.</hi> Now I would very faine know of any man (which ſhal be all the anſwer I ſhal give to this ſophiſtical cavil) whether by theſe words Aſtrologie, be convinced as uncertain, becauſe Mr. <hi>Briggs</hi> and another, or (ſuppoſe halfe a dozen more) could find no certainty therein; when <hi>Ptolomy, Galen, Hippocrates,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and thouſands more, found not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly certainty therein, but concluded and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed that it was the moſt beneficial and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Art under the Sunne; and whereas he cites <hi>Phavorinus</hi> againſt Aſtrologie in theſe words, <hi>Aut adverſa eventura dicunt, &amp;c.</hi> which is, <hi>They foretel either things of proſperity or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; if of proſperity, and they faile, then thou ſhalt be proſperous or happy in hoping for that good, if of adverſity, and hit not right, then thou wert miſerable in fearing in vaine, &amp;c.</hi> which agrees with what he ſayeth Mr. <hi>Briggs</hi> would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to do, <hi>viz To prove the rules of Aſtrologie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory, viz.</hi> It ſhal be ſo, and it ſhal not be ſo, which is the meereſt cavil of all the reſt, to ſay, <hi>Ergo</hi> Aſtrologie is uncertain. I wil under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take then a greater matter then Mr. <hi>Briggs,</hi> for let there be what Art or Science that Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> can deviſe nominated (though never ſo true) I wil undertake to ſpeak as much, nay and with more proof againſt it, then all theſe his learned men hath done in this <hi>his Character of the preſent times</hi> (he forgot to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169799:38"/>
put in thoſe that denie the truth; nay, and not onely ſo, but ſophiſtically and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly maintaine it to their utmoſt indeavours, thinking the citing of St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> to be proof enough to terrifie the Reader from underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this ſtudy, or continuing therein, not obſerving the words of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,<note place="margin">Looke the firſt Chapter of his treatiſe.</note> and together with the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> to include the <hi>Councels,</hi> but tels us not how and upon what grounds and reaſons they diſallowed of the Art, leſt then his malice be diſcovered. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me then for a concluſion, as wel to this Chapter, as his cavils, aske him theſe two queſtions; whether a man may not (if envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſpoſed) ſpeake againſt the moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt truths, nay againſt the very word of God, and wreſt the Scripture to their owne incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and intentions? And ſecondly, if he be proved hereof guilty, in the next Chapter, to wreſt the Scripture ſence to confute Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie; whether he be not more fit to be brought under the laſh of the Law, then Aſtrologers? ſo have you <hi>his learned men</hi> againſt Aſtrologie confuted; we come now to the maine point of all, <hi>viz.</hi> whether Aſtrologie be condemned by the word of God?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:169799:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Wherein his divine proofs againſt <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> are examined and confuted.</head>
               <p>BUt before I begin, I ſhall deſire the Reader to have a ſpecial care to remember what Aſtrologie is, which is now in controverſie, and either to be confuted and condemned, or defended and cleared; the definition whereof you have at the beginning of the firſt Chapter, for otherwiſe our paines and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are but frivolous on either ſide; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I commend Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> in that he did not firſt ſet downe the ſtate of his queſtion, before he began to confute it; but thinking <hi>pleno ore,</hi> to condemne Aſtrologie, will be enough to ſcare the Reader from the ſtudy thereof, leave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to conſider what it is he condemnes, although he be altogether ignorant of the ſame; that ſo his words may have the more force, and take the deeper impreſſion in the Readers heart to believe what he would faine, and as much as in him lies, ſtudies to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:169799:39"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Wherein his firſt Scripture proofe, <hi>viz. Deut. 18 verſe. 10.</hi> is convinced and cleared, no wiſe to condemne Aſtrologie.</head>
                  <p>COncerning his firſt proof, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10. I have formerly in my <hi>reply</hi> to <hi>Raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> Declaration againſt Aſtrologie ſayed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and referred the Reader, to that never to be enough honoured and remembred, the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi> to be further ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the reſt of his divine proofs, who in his anſwer to Mr. <hi>Chamber,</hi> hath ſo excellently and learnedly handled, that the wit of man is not able to performe better, and that ſo learned a piece may not be kept from the knowledge of the vulgar, under the cloud of ſilence, I wil here along in the confutation of Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his divine proofs, uſe his very arguments and words (as neare as I can) againſt the ſame places alleadged by Mr. <hi>Chamber.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">His firſt proofe of Scripture refelled.</note>His Firſt proof then is <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10. <hi>There ſhall not be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you any one that uſeth Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or an obſerver of times;</hi> which words ſaith he, by the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the learned of all ſorts, <hi>Signifie Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169799:39"/>
and Aſtrologers;</hi> and for the which ſinnes,<note place="margin">Look the ſeventh page of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to <hi>Raunce</hi> his Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</note> the Nations were driven out before the Children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Now that you ſhal ſee how farre Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> is miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to think hereby to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the world againſt Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie (as I ſayed before) I will give you that <hi>(learned, and never enough remembred) Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans words, againſt Mr.</hi> Chamber hereon, viz. Sir. <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon</hi> Knight,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>2.</hi> page <hi>41.</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his peece in defence of Aſtrologie againſt Mr. Chamber.</note> where he ſaith, <q>
                        <hi>Picus</hi> urgeth that <hi>Achinas</hi> underſtandeth the word in the Original, to ſignifie ſuch, as obſerve lucky and unlucky houres, which our Engliſh tranſlate, <hi>a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garder of times,</hi> and <hi>Tremelius, Planetarius,</hi> and from hence they think they have preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant evidence to condemne Aſtrologie by this Law.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I may reckon up here alſo Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his <hi>Mercer, R. Kimchy,</hi> and <hi>Schindler,</hi> who, ſaith he, take the words in the worſt ſence (which I may very wel ſay indeed, and ſhall appeare by and by) <hi>viz.</hi> The curious and Diabolical Arts, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Magi of the Egyptians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In the ſecond page of this treatiſe, you have it defined.</note> 
                     <hi>Ergo</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Homes,</hi> Aſtrologie is not lawful, but what affinity aſtrologie hath with <hi>Diabolical
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169799:40"/>
practiſes;</hi> I deſire the Reader to remember what Aſtrologie is. But to proceed with Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydons</hi> diſcourſe hereon, ſaith he, <q>But notwithſtanding all this, I wil make it appeare, that theſe Tranſlations are of ſmal force; and being admitted, little or no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing impeach this Art.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>And firſt, I incounter them with the authority of the Church, even from the time of <hi>Moſes</hi> until they wrote, being whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them. For to begin with the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> They have Tranſlated the word <hi>Gnonen,</hi> in this place <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth <hi>Augurare,</hi> or to divine by the voice and flying of Birds; St. <hi>Hierome</hi> and the vulga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> expounded it, of ſuch as divine by obſerva<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion by Dreames. <hi>Pagnine</hi> in his Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on interpreteth it <hi>Hariolus,</hi> by a general name, or ſuch a one, as divineth at the Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tar by ſacrifices. <hi>Arias Montanus,</hi> uſeth the word <hi>Praeſtigiator,</hi> that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Jugler or Coſiner,<note place="margin">All theſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſes is given to the word.</note> that wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Legerdemaine deceiveth the eye-ſight. (See that that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> alſo confeſſed by Mr. <hi>Hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> himſelfe) So that beſides a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> antiquity, and conſent of the whole Church againſt him, we ſee that di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vers men have diverſly interpreted the word; and therefore I leave it to the judge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169799:40"/>
of the Reader, whether we are to give credit to the new Expoſitors, rather then to the ancient and learned <hi>Hebrews</hi> themſelves, who beſt underſtood their own Language, or to the common underſtanding of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and the Church, even from the firſt, until theſe men (which hath been long ſince) expounded it otherwiſe then all that had gone before them.</q> And now to come to the Engliſh Tranſlation, as we have it expreſſed in our Bibles; ſee with what reaſon and ſound arguments Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> is ſilenced, who is not onely thus miſtaken in the ſignification of the word, but moſt ſlanderouſly intrudeth Aſtrologers with, or at leaſt makes them the ſame with Wizards, and thoſe that have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpirits, for ſaith he, <hi>So that indeed (as 'tis in</hi> Levit. 20.6.) <hi>to follow ſuch kinde of Arts,</hi> (ſpeaking before of Divination, by obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of times, and jugling which he all along concludes to be Aſtrologie, as his interpreters there have it) <hi>Is to goe a Whoring (ſpiritually) from Chriſt, and God will (ſaith he) ſet his face againſt ſuch, and cut off ſuch from among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, weighty reaſons againſt Aſtrologie</hi> (ſaith he) when the words of the Text are meerely wreſted by him, not having in the leaſt any mention of this Art, or Artiſts; but of thoſe that have familiar ſpirits, and Wizards, and how he wil prove Aſtrologers to be any of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169799:41"/>
theſe, I know not. Yet I can tell him when he wil doe it, though I never ſee him, and that is when he can make the 18. of <hi>Deut.</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the legality of Aſtrologie; but to come to our engliſh Tranſlation, the ſame Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon</hi> ſayeth, <q>Concerning our engliſh Tranſlators, I find they rather leave us in doubts, then reſolved; for whereas here they take the word <hi>Gnonen</hi> for a regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of times, in other places they interpret it otherwaies, as in 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> Chap. 33. verſ. 6. for Witchcraft, and in the 5. of <hi>Micah</hi> For South-ſayers. So that in this inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to themſelves, they muſt either give a better reaſon (then any thing I know they are able) why in this place of <hi>Deut.</hi> it ſhould not be interpreted as wel a <hi>Witch,</hi> or a <hi>Sooth-ſayer,</hi> as a <hi>regarder of times,</hi> or elſe they muſt underſtand ſuch a regarder of times, as makes his election by Witchcraft and Sooth-ſaying, and not by <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi> Againe, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the word be admitted as the Engliſh Tranſlate it; yet neither is all regarding of time prohibited, neither doth it prove that regarding of time by Aſtrologie is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. For <hi>Solomon</hi> (the wiſeſt of men) ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>That the heart of the wiſe man knowes time, and that to every purpoſe there is a time, as to Plant, to pluck up, to ſlaie, to heale, to breake downe, to build, to weepe, to laugh, &amp;c. which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169799:41"/>
none but the foole neglecteth.</hi>
                     </q> As in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> farther in the third Chap. and more at large: <q>and he that obſerveth not time, but ſhall laugh when he ſhould weep, and ſow when he ſhould reap, is unſeaſonable and maketh himſelf ridiculous, according to that of the Poet <hi>Virgil.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>"Multi ante occaſum maia caepere, ſed iſtos</l>
                     <l>"Expectata ſeges, vanis eluſit ariſtis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <q>Wherefore if this be the true interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſignification of the word, he muſt ſpeak againſt that ſuperſtitious obſervation of times, which the Heathen uſed, and that ſuperſtitious people at this preſent do uſe;</q> the very ſame I may ſay to Mr <hi>Homes,</hi> if he know any practitioner of the Art that maketh any ſuperſtitious uſe thereof, let him be brought forth and condemned, I'le aſſure him, he ſhall ſee me as ready to aſſiſt him therein, and be as forward as himſelf: <q>But that it can be applyed againſt obſerving of ſuch times as depend upon evident cauſes and reaſons in nature, which onely Aſtrologie preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth (as aboveſaid) none but that man that hath no judgement can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine:<note place="margin">Looke the <hi>2</hi> chapter of this Treatiſe where Aſtrologie is helpful o hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry.</note> And you have heard before <hi>Ptolomy</hi> himſelf as well as St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and all the beſt learned Aſtrologers do abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglect the ſuperſtitious and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169799:42"/>
ſortilegious elections of the Heathen: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reader ſeeth that this text (were the interpretation admitted) impugneth them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his expoſitors, take the interpretation of the word <hi>Gnonan,</hi> as the ſame Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon</hi> delivers it by Mr <hi>Edward Lively,</hi> profeſſour of the Hebrew in <hi>Cambridge</hi> to Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> 
                     <q>being a man (for his ſingular knowledge in all kind of good learning, but eſpecially in Divinity, and the tongues) of great eſtimation and authority in that Univerſity; who was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited by Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon</hi> to deliver his opinion and judgement of the Hebrew word, becauſe it was objected by Mr <hi>Chamber,</hi> that <hi>Tremelius</hi> did interpret it <hi>planetarius,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the Readers better ſatisfaction, I have hear delivered it <hi>verbatim</hi> as that worthy Knight hath it.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>I have looked in all the Hebrew Scripture, wherein that word is uſed, examining as well the judgements of the Hebrew <hi>Scoliaſtes</hi> in their Commentaries, as alſo many of the beſt tranſlations, <hi>Caldee, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> among whom for the ſignification of that word, I find this general agreement, that it ſignifieth an unlawfull and forbidden Art of Soothſaying, or Juggling, or Sorcery, or Witchcraft; but touching the certaine
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169799:42"/>
and ſpeciall kind thereof, there is ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention and diſagreement among them, as thereby it may ſufficiently appear, the very proper and clear ſignification thereof in <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> to be utterly unknown: for <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> in his Commentary upon the 19. Chapter of <hi>Levit.</hi> ver. 26. deriving it from the word <hi>Gnonan,</hi> which ſignifieth a cloud; under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood thoſe thereby who by the formes and movings of the clouds, foretold things to come: <hi>Avenarius</hi> from the ſame root under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Juglers which caſt a cloudy miſt before their eyes, to cover and hide their deceitful ſlights. R. <hi>Solomon</hi> on the ſame place referreth it to a word <hi>Gnonah,</hi> which noteth time, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ſuch to be meant, as took upon them to define times of good or bad luck for the doing of things; others fetching it from the word <hi>Gnanath,</hi> which ſignifieth to anſwer, underſtood Soothſayers, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked of ſecret matters, anſwered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their skill; as by like reaſon <hi>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioli</hi> were ſo called, <hi>quaſi farioli, a fando,</hi> as ſome of the ancient learned have obſerved: ſome from <hi>gnajin,</hi> ſignifying an eye, thought Juglers to be noted, which do <hi>perſtringere oculos,</hi> that their legerdemaine may not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be eſpied: here is great diverſity of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, but none commeth to <hi>Tremelius</hi> his mind, for a planetary,</q> (<hi>or of</hi> Mr Homes <hi>his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169799:43"/>
Arabrick</hi> verſions, which it ſeems he is loath or at leaſt aſhamed to nominate, yet he might as well have wronged them as <hi>Moſes,</hi> who, he ſaith, bringeth five ſtrong arguments againſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrological Art, when al the world cannot ſhew that in all thoſe verſes, <hi>viz.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, &amp; 16. of the 18. of <hi>Deut.</hi> nor indeed in the whole chap. that <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is ſo much as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) <q>yet ſome for a Jugler have agreed with him, which ſignification of this word, even <hi>Tremelius</hi> himſelf retaineth in the 19. Chap. of <hi>Levit.</hi> ver. 26. and in the 2. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> ver. 6. and divers other places, thereby ſhewing the vanity of his own planetarius: for if it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and truly ſignifieth <hi>Preſtigiatorem</hi> in any place, I dare boldly ſay, that it ſignifieth <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netarium</hi> in no place; I may here omit anota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place in the 57. chap. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> ver. 3. where this word is taken for Witchcraft, <hi>beni gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenah</hi> Witches children: So it is interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted in our <hi>Geneva</hi> tranſlation; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expounded by the Hebrew Doctors on that place, <hi>Jarchi</hi> and <hi>Chimchi;</hi> ſo tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Mr <hi>Calvine</hi> (a man for underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scripture, indued with an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable gift of judgement) <hi>filii veneficae,</hi> which by <hi>Kimchy</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be true by this reaſon,<note place="margin">Yet <hi>Mr Homes</hi> affirmeth <hi>Kim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> maketh mention of attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting good to one time and bad to another.</note> that the word <hi>Gnonenah</hi>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:169799:43"/>
there uſed is for the <hi>foeminine gender,</hi> pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Woman; becauſe women (ſaith he) for the moſt part are given to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing of this devilliſh Art, it were madneſs to thinke women ſhould have given them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſtudy of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> or Planetary aſpects (a thing never uſed in any Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth that ever I heard of) but for Witchery, every where to be found in them rife and common. Here therefore I end, for this matter confidently affirming, that neither <hi>Tremelius</hi> if he were alive, nor <hi>Junius,</hi> nor any for them can prove that <hi>Planetarius</hi> is the clear and ſure ſignification of <hi>Gnonen,</hi> in any place of Scripture.</q> Thus far Mr. <hi>Lively.</hi> And I may conclude this point with Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydons</hi> words next enſuing, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q>Wherefore I do conclude, that if that which is before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken be indifferently conſidered, there is no man able demonſtratively to argue to the condemnation of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> out of this text.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Wherein his ſecond proof is refelled, <hi>viz.</hi> Eſay <hi>2.6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ANd if ſo, or rather, ſeeing it is ſo, then I may with more confidence affirme his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169799:44"/>
paſſage of Scripture to be leſſe materiall in all reſpects, for the blindeſt of people may clearly ſee, it doth no whit (by his owne words, nay and argument) ſo much as either hint or mean <hi>Astrologie, Eſay</hi> 2.6. <hi>Therefore thou haſt forſaken thy people, the houſe of</hi> Jacob, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are repleniſhed from the Eaſt, and are Soothſayers like the Philiſtims;</hi> where is Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie in all this? the text tels us God had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken his people becauſe they were Soothſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but as for their being Aſtrologers, I ſee nothing mentioned: is not this a pretty ſcare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crow? thinking any paſſage of the Scripture enough to condemn <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> whether it ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of it or no? what does he thinke Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie to be Soothſaying? then he ſhould prove it ſo, and I will aſſure him I ſhall endeavour then to ſpeake as much againſt it as he can; but if it be not firſt proved ſo, this wreſt of Scripture and ſophiſticall cavill is already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felled; but he begins to make up the matter with the interpretations of ſome men, but all will not do, they are at leaſt a mile ſhort of the marke, yet if I ſhould ſee any of them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an inch thereof, I ſhould conclude him to be as fas from hitting it, as he that is a yard wide; but let us ſee but how he tugs to bring this far fetcht argument or proof to ſerve his turne; he ſhews us firſt that the word clearly ſignifieth Soothſayers, which is enough alone
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169799:44"/>
to refell all his Interpreters therein, let them ſay what they will to the contrary, <hi>Vatablus</hi> in his <hi>notes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>rendreth it Diviners;</hi> and <hi>Junius, Praeſtigiators, that is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that make ſhew of that they cannot do:</hi> you have heard <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> opinion but now, but what of this? <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablus</hi> ſaith the word <hi>imports Diviners,</hi> muſt this conſequently and infallibly be <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> why not <hi>Necromancers, Auguries, Inchanters, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, Auruſpicers?</hi> do not all theſe Divine? but I need not inſiſt longer hereon, for, he anſwers this point in his following words himſelf, <hi>the Septuagint</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>rendreth it</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>that is (ſaith Budeus)</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a kind of foretelling: as</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>(ſaith they) ſignifieth Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination, and generally the</hi> Caldee, Syriacke, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabicke, Arias montanus, &amp;c. <hi>renders it Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurers or Auguries, Ergo,</hi> not Aſtrologers, but ſaith he, <hi>farther becauſe antiquities tell us that that the Augurers did Divine as well by the aſpects of the heavens as by flying Birds; Authors of late times commonly uſe that word to expreſſe Divination in general:</hi> O brave reaſon! becauſe for brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſake in Oration, or the like, Authors (as he calleth them) perhaps uſe this word, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will uſe it (being as he confeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf general) to condemn particularly <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie?</hi> and becauſe the text ſpeaketh againſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurers, and they know the aſpects of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets; therefore, it alſo condemneth Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie?
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169799:45"/>
all that believe ſhall be ſaved (ſaith the Scripture) it is clear <hi>the Devils believe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> Ergo, I ſhall conclude them not damned? rare logick indeed! which is as affirmative, I'm confident, as his argument in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; ſo that you ſee then I hope by this time, the infatigable pains Mr <hi>Homes</hi> taketh to ſwim againſt the ſtreame, and when reaſon and truth will no wiſe ſupport him, he laies hold juſt as he is ſinking, on the ruſhes and weak props and ſupporters of logick, which neither is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſave him, but together with him they ſink down with perpetual ſhame and ſilence, into the pit of forgetfulneſſe: Alas poor Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Homes;</hi> I muſt confeſſe this would make any one <hi>Pitty the poore Paſtor.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A pretty jeſt, of a zealous Prieſt.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Wherein his third text is convinced, <hi>viz.</hi> Eſay <hi>44.25.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THirdly, he produceth the 44. Chapter of <hi>Eſay,</hi> verſe 25, &amp;c. <hi>I am the Lord thy redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which do fruſtrate the ſignes of Wizards, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Soothſayers mad, foiling their wiſe men, and making their skil fooliſh:</hi> This is to as little
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169799:45"/>
purpoſe brought to condemn Aſtrologie, as it is weakneſſe in him to alleadge it or affirme it: but before I begin to meddle with the words, I thinke meet here firſt to remove his injurious wrong he doth impoſe upon Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers, to reckon them Soothſayers and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, Diviners, or Augurers, &amp;c. But I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire here the reader to obſerve that Mr <hi>Homes</hi> in his book, ſtudieth to condemn thoſe that profeſſe Aſtrologie here in <hi>England,</hi> and this City of <hi>London,</hi> and yet he will needs intrude Aſtrologie, or rather perſwade the vulgar, that Aſtrologie is the ſame with theſe above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; from all which Aſtrologie is as far, as black from white, or <hi>Mary-ſtainings</hi> from <hi>Bred-ſtreet,</hi> or as different as a<note n="a" place="margin">A very Religious ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (if rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) of a Divine and one that ſhould with ſuch zeal ſet forth the ſins of the times.</note> 
                     <hi>ſick bodie</hi> is from one that's <hi>well:</hi> which becauſe he can bring ſome proof againſt them, will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore terme <hi>Astrologers,</hi> by the ſame to be underſtood; when all <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> will not deny to condemn (in as much as in them lies) theſe aforeſaid ſtudies as well as he. But to the purpoſe, how can Mr <hi>Homes,</hi> or any one living, prove <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> to be ſignified by any of theſe names, when it is clear (as aboveſaid) it dependeth meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the natural influences and effects of the Stars? which is not to foretel by the flying or
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169799:46"/>
voice of Birds, obſervation of the intrals of Beaſts, and the like; nor indeed is it proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be termed <hi>Divination,</hi> for to divine is not, or doth not naturally ſignifie the foretelling of future events by natural cauſes, but by ſome divine inſtinct. Wherefore Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> might have diſcharged his duty much better both to God and his Country, if he had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed his pen to vent all the Gall both in his Inckhorn, heart and brain, againſt thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the truth, that maintain their owne opinions, before the word of God, and make no Conſcience of perjury, profeſſing the form of Godlineſſe, but (in effect) denying the power thereof. And not againſt Aſtrologers (nor the Art) who attribute all their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the power of the Stars to the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Creator of them; and in all points of Religion, ſhew themſelves conformable both to the diſcipline of the Church, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Laws of the Land.</p>
                  <p>But to come to the words in the Text, which he would needs inforce againſt Aſtrologie; the ſame Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi> further ſayeth upon theſe words. <q>That they are purpoſely uttered to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the omnipotency of God,<note place="margin">Page <hi>32.</hi> Chap. <hi>2.</hi> of his defence of Aſtrologie.</note> ſo greatly diminiſhed by Idolatry, but to imagine that God would ſet forth the greatnes of his power, by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169799:46"/>
the ſame againſt that, which in it's ſelf is fruitleſſe, infirme, and of no force at all, were not onely againſt ſence, but in truth to fruſtrate the words and meaning of God himſelf; wherefore it doth neceſſarily follow, that ſo long as it pleaſeth him to ſuffer the courſe of nature to proceed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interruption, <hi>Aſtrological ſignes muſt be confeſſed effectual,</hi> and not to be fruſtrated but by miracle, and by his omnipotent power, to which that the Starres are ſubject, all our Aſtrologers do confeſſe, and none but an Atheiſt wil deny. For as God is the Creator of all things, ſo is he the firſt cauſe of all cauſes, to whom all cauſes are but his inſtruments; and therefore as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument worketh not of it ſelf, but when it is imployed by the Artificer, ſo the heavens being Gods inſtruments, doe not exerciſe their force upon theſe inferiour things, but as God doth uſe their miniſtery in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the world.</q> And this he ſayeth is taught us by the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> (as above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) Chap. 2.21.22. where (ſaith he) he ſayeth, <q>not ſimply, <hi>the heavens ſhall heare the earth,</hi> but firſt, <hi>I wil heare the heavens,</hi> to ſhew them the power the heavens have over the earth, and that it dependeth on God. In which ſence, the Scripture ſayeth alſo, <hi>God worketh all in all things, and that we live,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169799:47"/>
move, and have our being in him.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether we reſpect the natural courſe of things, or thoſe accidents which happen beſides the order of nature, we are to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it to be the ſupereminent power of God, as the firſt cauſe of every thing, which nevertheleſſe can be no impeachment to Aſtrologie, becauſe God doth govern ordinately, and therefore ſeldome perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth or diſturbeth that order, whereby in his eternal providence, he doth govern his workmanſhip.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore ſeeing he can not properly make the words above-ſaid to ſignifie Aſtrologie, and ſeeing the Text doth not in the leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Aſtrologers, but onely <hi>Sooth-ſayers,</hi> and <hi>Wizards;</hi> I may confidently affirme and conclude this Text no whit at all to impeach Aſtrologie; and then conſequently his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be meerely ſophiſtical, raſh, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate, malicious, weak, and inconſiſtent with either reaſon, ſence or honeſty. This may ſufficiently ſerve to refel this his wreſt of Scripture, but if the Reader deſireth further the diſcuſſion hereof, and how it is in every point cleared and handled, let him peruſe the 2 Chapter of Sir <hi>Christopher Heydons</hi> defence of Aſtrologie againſt Mr. <hi>Chamber,</hi> to whom (for brevities ſake) I refer him, where you ſhall not onely finde theſe his owne reaſons and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169799:47"/>
words, but likewiſe the opinions and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of as wel the Ancient as latter Divines; all which could never pick any thing in the leaſt, juſtly to be objected againſt <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi> Ye ſee clearly therefore Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miſtake, or at leaſt wilful wreſt of the Text; to ſerve his owne turne, to condemne Aſtrologie, but all wil not do, which is a moſt pittiful caſe, and doth almoſt perſwade me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, to <hi>Pitty the poore Paſtor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Wherein his fourth proofe is refelled, <hi>viz. Eſay 47.12.13.14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FOurthly, he brings the 47. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> 12.13.14. <hi>Stand now with thine Inchantments, and with the multitude of thy Sorceries, Let now the Aſtrologers, the Star-gazers, the monthly Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators, ſtand up and ſave thee, &amp;c. Behold they ſhal be as ſtubble, the fire ſhall burn them, they ſhall not deliver themſelves, &amp;c.</hi> This very place (as I would have the Reader obſerve) is enough to confute his former injury to Aſtrologers, in reckoning them no other then <hi>Sooth-ſayers, Wizards, Sorcerers</hi> and the like, when he ſees clearly the Lord here makes a particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between the one and the other; for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169799:48"/>
you ſee, <hi>Aſtrologers, Monthly Prognoſticators, Sorceries,</hi> and <hi>Inchanters,</hi> particularly named, here I may alſo put the Reader in mind,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his craft in wreſting the Scripture.</note> that he take him as he is, <hi>viz.</hi> a Sophiſter, in wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the Scripture to his own purpoſe, and interpreting it to maintaine theſe his arguments, which he cannot otherwiſe in the leaſt ſupport with either reaſon or truth.</p>
                  <p>But to come now to the claring of the Text, which he thinks doth abſolutely ſtrike the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal blow to Aſtrologie; inferring from thence, that <hi>Aſtrologie is oppoſite to confidence in God,</hi> and that Aſtrologers are <hi>much of the ſame abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, with Inchanters and Sooth-ſayers,</hi> (which you may ſee is falſe, and as for Sooth-ſayers they are not in the leaſt mentioned in the Text, where you ſee he againe hath his owne interpretation) <hi>and that they are to be derided, and no wiſe to be truſted in, &amp;c.</hi> But as I ſayed before, the wit of man is not able to anſwer theſe his vaine wreſts and interpretations of the Scriptures, better then by that Honourable Gentleman, Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi> I heare give you, as he hath it in his 2. Chapter, in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Chamber,</hi> bringing the ſame place of Scripture, and indeed with the ſame conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as doth Mr. <hi>Homes.</hi> 
                     <q>I wil not deny that, becauſe God and his Prophets were not beleeved by the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> (who repoſed in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169799:48"/>
their <hi>Magicians, Sooth-ſayers,</hi> and <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians</hi>) the Prophet here in a ſcorning <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſmus,</hi> biddeth them ſave their Empire from ruine, therein contemning their <hi>Power,</hi> and not their <hi>Predictions,</hi> and expreſly noting that it ſhall not be in them to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the judgements to come. This I do plainly acknowledge, although were I diſpoſed to ſtand upon all advantages with Mr. <hi>Chamber,</hi> ſith both <hi>Vatablus,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> in their Commentaries, confeſſe that word <hi>Chabar,</hi> doth indifferently ſignifie ſuch obſervers of heaven as were <hi>Inchanters</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; I could eaſily avoid him as not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting <hi>ad idem,</hi> ſith not Aſtrologers ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but ſuch as withall joyned <hi>Magick,</hi> ſeemes here to be mentioned. And it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> and of <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Balacke,</hi> that though they were Aſtrologers, yet they repoſed their ſafety againſt God and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, onely in their Magical power, by which (as their Poets and others report) they profeſſe themſelves able to pull the Moon and the Stars out of Heaven, and ſo doth <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> teſtifie, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. that though they were cunning in Aſtrologie, yet they did onely prevent the evils which they did fore-ſee, by <hi>Inchantments</hi> and <hi>Charmes.</hi> For in truth, <hi>Aſtrologie profeſſeth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169799:49"/>
onely to fore-ſee natural mutations and accidents, and not power to prevent and ſave.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Nota bene.</note> But to returne to that which he moſt expects, I will admit as much as Mr. <hi>Chamber</hi> himſelf can deſire, that the Prophet here derideth the <hi>truſt</hi> which was put in the <hi>skil</hi> of <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in this fore going Text.</note> 
                        <hi>(which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Mr.</hi> Homes <hi>his chief drift alſo</hi>) now let him frame his argument, and he ſhall never be able to bring the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of this Chap. (which is, <hi>That Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity and Aſtrologie cannot ſtand together</hi>) (which indeed is Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> his argument al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo concluding Aſtrologie, to be <hi>oppoſite to confidence in God</hi>) within his concluſion. For it followeth not, that becauſe upon ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance a thing my be derided, that it is unlawful. If this were any conſequence, then becauſe <hi>confidences in Princes, Pſal.</hi> 1.16. <hi>in Riches, Pſal.</hi> 52. <hi>in Horſes and Chariots, Eſay</hi> 31. <hi>in Cities, Jer.</hi> 5. <hi>in Phyſitians,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. <hi>in Negotiation or trade of Merchandize.</hi> In the laſt verſe of this ſame Chapter of <hi>Eſay,</hi> (where the very ſame words and phraſe are uſed againſt Merchants, that before were uſed againſt <hi>obſervers of heaven,</hi> or Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as <hi>Arias Montanus and Tremelius</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it) is prohibited, derided, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; we muſt hold the <hi>permiſſion of Princes,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169799:49"/>
Riches, Horſes, Chariots, Cities, Phyſitians</hi> and <hi>Merchants,</hi> to be againſt Chriſtianity, and unlawful. He ought therefore firſt to have diſtinguiſhed of the truſt that is here deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and not thus to deceive by any <hi>elench, à dicto ſecundum quid ad dictum ſimpliciter,</hi> as if all truſt were taken away, becauſe ſome truſt is derided. For in theſe places, and the like, onely ſuch a truſt as excludeth confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God is underſtood, and no other. As in our caſe, where notwithſtanding God by his Prophets had threatned the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Babyloniſh Monarchy, it was not believed; but theſe heathen preſuming ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon their owne power and skil, in contempt of God broke forth, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth verſe 10. into theſe blaſphemous ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>None ſeeth me. Quaſi dieat (ſayeth</hi> Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius) <hi>ne deus quidem novit rationes meas, nay God himſelfe knoweth not my waies,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>I am and none elſe,</hi> and verſe 7. <hi>I ſhall not ſit as a Widow, nor ſhall not know the loſſe of Children:</hi> Thus denying both God and his power, while they preſume upon their owne. But is this heatheniſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and confidence to be imputed as a fault to Aſtrologie? or is it not truly to be reputed the impiety of the profeſſors, and others, with whom the Prophet dealeth? who denying that to God which is due, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169799:50"/>
aſcribing more then they ought to the Stars, and their own knowledge and power, doe that which Aſtrologie never taught them, and therefore is not guilty of their ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.<note place="margin">This had beene well done of Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> alſo.</note> He ought then to make a difference between the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, with whom the Prophet hath to doe, and Chriſtians againſt whom he writeth; for though it be true that Chriſtian Aſtrologers do monthly prognoſticate, as is mentioned in the Text, by the conſideration of the Stars; yet is he not able to tax any of them with that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation from God, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety,<note place="margin">The difference between Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers and thoſe that are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Text.</note> which is here derided. For to place confidence in Stars, as in divine cauſes and powers, is one thing, and to eſteeme them but as ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate and ſecond cauſes in nature, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the one maketh them Gods, the other but Gods inſtruments, which (as our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers doe acknowledge with one conſent) it is in his power to alter,<note place="margin">Nota bene.</note> as beſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his divine will; and therefore they are very far from that heatheniſh preſumption and confidence here taxed, whereby ye may ſee, <hi>that the trust may be reproved, yet the Art unchecked.</hi> For I omit here to ſhow, that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169799:50"/>
monthly prognoſtications grounded upon obſervation, deduced from cauſes in nature,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> have ever been permitted and ſuffered, in all wel ordered and Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, ſo far as I know; and that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and thoſe latter Divines by me before remembred, but even Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelfe, in his admonition, with others (that attribute as little as they may to this Art) do allow thereof, ſo far forth as they extend to the ſtate of the <hi>Weather,</hi> of <hi>Health, Plagues, Plenty, Dearth,</hi> and to the direction of the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> when to <hi>Purge</hi> by <hi>Pill,</hi> when by <hi>Potion,</hi> when <hi>by letting of blood;</hi> this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as far as our prognoſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions proceed;<note place="margin">Nota.</note> which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe would not have been ſuffered, if God by his holy Prophet had ſhewed any deteſtation thereof, or reproved the ſame as unlawfull, and unchriſtian. Wherefore when theſe adverſaries condemn the Art for the abuſes of Artiſts, <hi>it is cleare that they do but play the ſophiſters,</hi> deceiving by a plain fallacy, <hi>ab accidente.</hi> And laſtly, if it be conſidered what St. <hi>Hierom, Hugo, Aquinas, Lyra, Haymo,</hi> and other ancient Expoſiters,<note place="margin">More you may read in the ſecond Chapter of his booke.</note> have written upon this Text, it is moſt certain, that not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169799:51"/>
one of them is ſo ſharp ſighted as to eſpie out any thing in this place that may prejudicate <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> but they all defend the ſame as fully as my ſelf.</q> Wherefore if in this proof of Scripture Mr <hi>Homes</hi> be not as far miſtaken as in all the reſt of his fore-going cavils, and maketh not himſelf appear to the eyes of the world to be a meere ſophiſter, let the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, judge: for I dare confidently affirm, that by the concluſion of this his cavill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this text, he is as ignorant in the Art of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> as from the true ſenſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Prophet; or from <hi>the art of adminiſtring Phyſick to ſick women,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">He is known to be a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Doctor.</note> nay I am moſt confident he is herein farther a great deal out of the way, then it is from <hi>Mary-ſtainings to Bred-ſtreet,</hi> wherefore I cannot chuſe but <hi>Pitty the poor Paſter,</hi> both for his miſtake, and abſolute miſſe of his plot and purpoſe, both of the one, and the other: I proceed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to his next Scripture proof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:169799:51"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Wherein his fifth proof is proved weak, as to his purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Jer. <hi>10.2, 3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIfthly, he ſtrives to condemn <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> by the 10. of <hi>Jer.</hi> v. 2, 3. but to as little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as in all the reſt, but with no leſs craft and deceit, Juglar-like, he indeavours to caſt the miſt of errour and miſtake before the eyes of his reader, that ſo he may carry on his deſign with more dexterity and agility: the words are, <hi>Learn not the way of the Heathen, and be not diſmaied at the ſignes of heaven, for the Heathen are diſmaied at them, &amp;c.</hi> whereupon he infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Aſtrologie not to be lawful,</hi> (becauſe as he thinks God here by the Prophet prohibiteth the <hi>Jewes</hi> to give credit to the Star-gazers) but as I ſaid before,<note place="margin">Aſtrologers hold no fatal neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity in the Stars.</note> 
                     <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do not make the Stars gods, but Gods inſtruments; not in the leaſt attributing fatall neceſſity to be in their power: wherefore then conſequently he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth not againſt, nor contradicteth, nor condemneth <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> by theſe his cavils, ſince they are as far from being guilty thereof as himſelf, nay and I believe more; for certainly he that will wreſt the Scripture to condemn what he underſtandeth not, meerly to ſhew himſelf <hi>a Time-ſerver,</hi> (as it is known ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169799:52"/>
Mr <hi>Homes</hi> is) is a hypocrite, and much to be feared whether he is not altogether as ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of God, as of this Art: But for the farther clearing of the text, and the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Mr <hi>Homes</hi> his miſtake, if not wilfull malice, let us hear what the ſame Sir <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Heydon</hi> ſaith in anſwer to the ſame place of Scripture alledged by Mr <hi>Chamber</hi> alſo to condemn <hi>Aſtrologie:</hi> 
                     <q>Whereupon Mr <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> inferreth, <hi>that the Prophet willeth the</hi> Jews <hi>to give no credit to the Star-gazers,</hi> (and Mr Homes, <hi>truſt or confidence,</hi> page 134, <hi>oppoſite to the confidence and comfort in God:</hi>) But ſure he that maketh this collection out of theſe words of the text, never (I think) either gazed or looked upon them with half an eye: <hi>for the Prophet prohibiteth fear,</hi> Mr Chamber, <hi>credit,</hi> (Mr Homes <hi>truſt or confidence;</hi>) again the Prophet ſpeaketh of the Stars themſelves, Mr Chamber <hi>of the perſons that obſerve them,</hi> (ſo Mr <hi>Homes</hi> alſo) wherefore what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is between the one and the other, ſo far ought we to be from giving Mr <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> aſſertion any credit (and how ſhall Mr <hi>Homes</hi> his then take?)</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>For if he will truly informe the reader, he knoweth there is nothing prohibited in theſe words, but that the <hi>Jews ſhould not learn the way of the Heathen;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The meaning of the text.</note> which when he wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169799:52"/>
againſt <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> he doth both ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be out of the way, and to ſeeke to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce others, for to the <hi>creature,</hi> as in theſe words, <hi>fear, not the ſignes of heaven;</hi> where the word <hi>fear,</hi> is not ſimply underſtood, <hi>but for Religious reverence, and Divine worſhip:</hi> for that it is often taken in this ſence, is no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty to thoſe that are acquainted with the ſpeech and phraſe of the holy Ghoſt: As for example, <hi>Eſay</hi> chap. 29. verſe 13. <hi>And their fear towards me, was taught by the precept of men: where fear is</hi> (by Chriſt himſelf, alleadging this place of the Prophet, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. v. 9.) expounded for <hi>worſhip,</hi> ſaying, <hi>in vain they worſhip me, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for doctrines, mens traditions:</hi> As likewiſe the very ſame word is uſed in other places, for the Idolatrous worſhip exhibited to falſe gods: as 2 <hi>Kings</hi> chap. 17. verſe 7. <hi>when the children of Iſrael ſinned, &amp;c.</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>they fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red other gods.</hi> I could confirm this by infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite like teſtimonies, were it not ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſo clear a caſe: But to prove that the Prophet even here, under this word, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe revoketh the <hi>Jews</hi> from worſhipping the heavenly bodies, is yet more evident by the words following: for after he hath in the two next verſes, expreſſed the vain cuſtomes of the Heathen, in erecting and adoring thoſe Images which they worſhipped; he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reſtraineth them from this ſecond Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169799:53"/>
ver. 5. in the very ſame phraſe, that he did at the firſt: <hi>fear them not, for they ſtand up as the Palm tree, but they ſpeak not, &amp;c.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by there is no colour of wrangling left to him, that diſpoſeth not himſelf to be obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately perverſe: but of force it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that the <hi>Jewes</hi> are here onely forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to imitate the Heathen in both theſe kinds of Idolatry.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This may clearly ſatisfie any juditious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial eye, for the clearing of this proof of Scripture, and that notwithſtanding it, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> doth ſtand in its full force no whit more eclipſed, (if ſo much) then the Sun, by being overcaſt with a cloud: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let all <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> proceed in their ſtudy in this heavenly and moſt lawful Art, except there could be more palpable witneſſe againſt it, then hath been hitherto produced. But to confirm what hath been already ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this text, let us hear what this worthy man further ſaith. <q>To confirm this more fully, by the conſideration of other places: the Scripture giveth us plentiful teſtimony, that the <hi>Jews</hi> did follow the Heathen in their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry to the Stars, but are never reprehended for learning <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> of them: Wherefore the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> chap. 5. propheſied to them long before, even this captivity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were held in <hi>Jeremies</hi> time,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169799:53"/>
                        <hi>becauſe they had born</hi> (that is worſhipped) <hi>the Images of Siccuth and Chiun. Abenezra</hi> and and with him <hi>Montanus,</hi> underſtanding the Planet <hi>Saturne</hi> by <hi>Chiun:</hi> and St. <hi>Hierome</hi> expounding this word <hi>Coeab,</hi> thinketh it to be <hi>Venus</hi> whom even the <hi>Saracens</hi> in his time did worſhip: But St. <hi>Luke,</hi> Acts 7. ver. 42. &amp; 43. following the Greeke doth explaine <hi>Amos,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>then God turned himſelf away, and gave them up to ſerve the hoſt of heaven, as it is written in the booke of the Prophets: and you tooke up the tabernacle of</hi> Moloch, <hi>and the Star of your God</hi> Remphaim, <hi>figures which you made to worſhip them, therefore I will carry you away beyond Babylon:</hi> and therefore not unaptly have ſome expoſitors conceived the Images by which the Prophet doth here exprobrate the Heathen, to have been the Images of the <hi>Signes,</hi> and that not without reaſon; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that after the Prophet hath reſtrained them from this Heatheniſh fear of the Sgnes, immediately he giveth this reaſon, <hi>for the cuſtomes of the people are vaine:</hi> and declaring wherein, he addeth, <hi>for one cutteth down a tree in the Forreſt, &amp;c.</hi> which ſhould want ſence, if this verſe depended not on the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: thus alſo 2 <hi>Kings</hi> chap. 17. verſes 15, 16. the hiſtory ſaith, <hi>they followed the Heathen that were round about them, concerning whom the Lord had charged them, that they ſhould not do
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169799:54"/>
like them:</hi> But now if Mr <hi>Chamber</hi> would know, wherein the Imitation of the Heathen offended God, the ſpirit of God himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth him, that this was not in the ſtudy of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> but <hi>in that they left the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord their God, and made them mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Images, even two Calves, and made a grove, and worſhiped all the hoſt of heaven, and ſerved Baal:</hi> Wherefore in the 23. chap. 4, 5, 11. of the ſame booke of the <hi>Kings,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> are again particularly reproved <hi>for offering incenſe to the ☉, <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> and Planets, and for dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting horſes and chariots to the Sun:</hi> and to return to our own Prophet; doth he not chap. 7. verſe 18. <hi>expreſly teſtifie, that their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren gather wood, their fathers kindle the fire, their women knead the dough, to make cakes for the Queen of heaven, and to powre out drink-offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to their gods?</hi> and is it not for this defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, not for <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> that he doth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe threaten, chap. 8. verſe 2. <hi>that the bones of their Kings, Princes, Prophets, Prieſts, and Inhabitants, ſhall be ſpread before the Sun and the Moon, and all the hoſt of heaven; whom they have followed, and whom they have ſerved, and whom they have followed, and whom they have ſought, and whom they have worſhipped?</hi> to be ſhort, the Prophet remembreth their like Idolatry to the hoſt of heaven, ch. 19. ver. 13. &amp; ch. 44.15. all which conſidered, it is plain enough
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169799:54"/>
why the Prophet in this 10. chap. ſeeketh to withdraw the <hi>Jewes from fearing the Signes of heaven,</hi> ſith in every place their Idolatry to heavenly bodies, is reprehended; <hi>But their imitation of the heathen in the ſtudy of Aſtrologie no where.</hi>
                     </q> But for tediouſneſſe I might here give you the expoſitions of the chiefeſt and beſt Expoſitors as he alſo ſets them down, who from all ages have interpreted the text in this ſenſe, but theſe my labours would then ſwell to a greater bulke, then I would willingly they ſhould; beſides it would be in ſome ſenſe ſuperfluous, ſith what hath been already ſaid may ſatisfie any one who doth not willingly blind his eyes, and abſolutely deny ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; wherefore I refer the curious reader <hi>to his moſt learned booke,</hi> chap. 2. and haſten to Mr <hi>Homes</hi> his remaining ſophiſtications.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VI. <hi>Wherein his ſixth proof is refelled,</hi> viz. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</head>
                  <p>HIs ſixth wreſt of Scripture is <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c. where we read <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> dreamed a dreame, and for to underſtand the interpretation and meaning of the dreame, he commanded to call all the <hi>Magitians, Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169799:55"/>
Sorcerers, &amp;c.</hi> before him, to tell him the ſignification of his dreame; which if they could not do, they ſhould be cut in pieces, &amp;c. upon which Mr <hi>Homes</hi> infers, that becauſe they could not ſhew the King his dreame, with the interpretation thereof, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is falſe, which I may ſay is a very falſe aſſertion; for if he had known what <hi>Astrologie</hi> is, he had never thus made himſelf ridiculous to condemn <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> by this aſſertion or place of Scripture, the reader may remember what <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie</hi> is,<note place="margin">Page <hi>2.</hi> it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined.</note> and how far all <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers</hi> hold it effectuall; as ye have alſo before. Now that this place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth no wiſe condemn <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> I ſhall deſire him to obſerve, that God in his ſecret wiſdome and counſel, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.18. had decreed what ſhould happen in the latter daies, and had revealed it to the King by a dreame, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſubverſion of his Monarchy, and together with his, all others whatſoever, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt which is the <hi>ſtone cut out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands,</hi> which afterwards <hi>grew to a mountain which filled the whole earth,</hi> both with his power and glory, by the clear Sun-ſhine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; by which I am confident Mr <hi>Homes</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove then, <hi>Astrologie</hi> to be condemned or to be falſe, when it is not in its power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale the ſecrets of God, but onely extendeth to the knowledge of natural accidents and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169799:55"/>
mutations, and their cauſes; which was not (you clearly ſee) the Kings dreame, but a revelation of Gods ſecret will and intent by dreame: wherefore ſince his argument will not hold, his concluſion muſt needs faile him. Moreover you ſee, as the dreame was really a revelation, ſo was alſo the interpretation thereof, for you ſee in that ſame ſecond chap. that <hi>Daniel</hi> prayed to God to reveal it unto him, which you ſee according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was in a viſion by night,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Daniel</hi> an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologer and Magician.</note> and thought he was as great an <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> and <hi>Magician</hi> as any of the wiſe men; yet he knowing it was a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret beyond nature, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.13, 14. applyed himſelf to God for the revelation thereof, not to the ſearch thereof in any booke of naturall cauſes, as of Aſtrologie or Magick: wherefore you ſee how far Mr <hi>Homes</hi> runs himſelf into an errour, for want of knowing what <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is, and the extent thereof. And then laſtly, he as raſhly concludes with his divine proofs, as in all his progreſſe before; intruding and falſely impeaching <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> to be ſome of thoſe that brought and burnt their books upon repentance of their wicked practices,<note place="margin">Acts 19.19.</note> which I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe (were they as he alſo moſt raſhly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately tearmes them to be, and as he
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169799:56"/>
ſaith ſet forth in the 21. <hi>Revel.</hi> 8. <hi>to have their parts in the lake that burneth with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi>) they had at that time done very well in burning their books, had they been worth a thouſand times as much againe as they are there reputed or valued at; but ſith their Art and ſtudy depends upon onely the knowledge of the nature and influences and motions of the Stars; I know not what reaſon he hath to include them to be thus penitent for ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nature onely, <hi>Ergo,</hi> not condemned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the word <hi>Sorcery</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> 21.8. wherefore ſeeing this is ſo apparently falſe, I ſhould counſel him (and that ſpeedily to) to burn his books that thus hath lead him into an errour, and to contradict the Scriptures; for I find in that very 21. of <hi>Revelation</hi> 8. <hi>Lyers</hi> expreſly nominated, and when he goeth to the fire with his books, let him remember to go by <hi>Bred-ſtreet,</hi> that ſo he may ſorrow for all together: that ſo the Lord may have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and <hi>Pitty of the poor Paſtor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:169799:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Wherein his reaſons and arguments againſt Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, is particularly examined and condemned, neither to conſiſt with reaſon or truth.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Wherein his firſt four-fold reaſon is convinced.</head>
                  <p>HIs firſt reaſon then is, (to prove Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie is falſe) that Aſtrologers themſelves confeſſe, <hi>that either the prudence of a moral wiſe man, or the piety of a Godly man, or the tutelarity of Angels, or the providence of God, over-ruling all things, may prevent their predictions. Whereupon be concludes that</hi> Aſtrologie is falſe; <hi>for ſaith he, what humane providence cannot doe, grace can; if not, Angels may; and wehre all faile, providence doth order according to the mind of God, &amp;c.</hi> To anſwer this his moſt weak cavil, I ſhall begin with what he ſets down laſt, viz. <hi>The providence of God over-ruling all things,</hi> which he ſayeth himſelfe (as well as the other three clauſes) is the conceſſion of Aſtrologers themſelves, and if ſo, I would demand then what advantage he hath hereby, againſt Aſtrologie; when he
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169799:57"/>
can ſay no more againſt it, then what the Practitioners in the Art do confeſs themſelves? there is certainly none but wretched Atheiſts, that will deny, that God hath not an over-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and a reſtraining power over all things, as well celeſtial, as terreſtrial; but whether his will and pleaſure be to alter their naturall courſes, is a queſtion, but he hath heard that <hi>Ptolomy</hi> himſelfe, nay and all Aſtrologers in general, do attribute nothing (farther then natural things, which are in ſublunary ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary bodyes) to the power and influence of the Stars;<note place="margin">The Stars have power but on na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural things.</note> he might then as well have ſayed, the eye hath no power to ſee, or diſtinguiſh from black and white, (becauſe by the power of ſenſe, it may be cloſed) as weakly to infer the Stars not to have power, becauſe God can alter, or is able to alter their motions, influences and effects, <hi>or the piety of a Godly man,</hi> which neither is in the verge of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all Aſtrologers will condeſcend and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that the Stars (as alſo <hi>Ptolomy</hi> himſelf) hath no power of what is beyond nature; and if piety be not as far beyond nature, as heaven is from earth, let the weakeſt capacity judge. He might then as well have ſaid, a fiſh is no living creature, nor hath any life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will not live on the Land; for it is altogether as far out of the element (as I may
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169799:57"/>
ſay) of the Stars, or their power to extend their influence to divine matters, as for a fiſh to fly, or a ſtone to ſwim, or the like ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous things, (if affirmed) which is contrary to nature. Wherefore his third clauſe alſo, is to as little effect, as the two former, when all that knows any thing in divinity, will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>tutelarity or guard of Angels,</hi> to be adminiſtred onely to the elect; and if this be not as far out of the bounds and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of nature as the other, I would deſire Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> to make cleare to the contrary; and for his fourth clauſe, it is as witty an one, as if one ſhould ſay, Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> is no Divine,, becauſe he is not as yet a Biſhop,<note n="k" place="margin">Inquire of Mr. <hi>Homes.</hi>
                     </note> or that a man is not marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe he lives from his wife. <hi>The prudence of a moral wiſe man, may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or prevent the effects of the Stars.</hi> This is not onely confeſſed by all the learned in Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, but alſo <hi>ſapiens dominabitur aſtris, a wiſe man may rule the Stars;</hi> but they do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore they have no effects at all, as the ignorant in the Art do with Mr. <hi>Homes;</hi> but they farther ſay, <hi>aſtra regunt homines, ſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git aſtra deus. The Stars rule men, but God ruleth the Stars;</hi> this is the doctrine of Aſtrologers (I meane thoſe that are Aſtrologers indeed, and know the fundamentals and true ground of the Art, not ſuch ignorant Practitioners
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169799:58"/>
as Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> and <hi>Raunce</hi>) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they mean,<note place="margin">Aſtrologers hold no fatal neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</note> when they ſay, <hi>aſtra regunt homines,</hi> any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal neceſſity to be attributed to thoſe heavenly bodies, nor to have power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver men, further then ſuch men are guided only by ſence as bruit beaſts, and not by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for they further affirm, that they <hi>niſi agunt, non cogunt,</hi> they <hi>act, or incline, but no wiſe compel;</hi> but where grace or reaſon ſupports a man, there, or on ſuch a man, the Stars have no power; wherefore then (by the way) I may aske Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> or <hi>Raunce,</hi> if they with all their <hi>pretended zeale,</hi> can find fault with this Doctrine, or teach better themſelves; or whether any Divine whatſoever, or all put together, can in the leaſt carp at this; or whether Aſtrologie then be <hi>Diabolical, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, the Doctrine or Language of the Devils, or wicked,</hi> as theſe two <hi>ſeeming zealous blades,</hi> moſt <hi>falſely, maliciouſly, inconſiderately,</hi> and <hi>ignorantly traduce it?</hi> and then I demand, ſince as the Philoſopher ſayeth, ignorance is the enemie of all good learning,<note place="margin">Ignorance the mother of vice.</note> whether they deſerve not exemplary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to condemne ſo <hi>noble,</hi> ſo <hi>profitable to the Common-wealth,</hi> ſo <hi>excellent,</hi> ſo <hi>divine,</hi> and ſo <hi>pleaſing a ſtudy, as Aſtrologie is,</hi> teaching and traducing their vile ignorance to the world; and truly as one of them <hi>moſt</hi>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:169799:58"/>
wiſely ſayed, if he ſhould make appeare what he knoweth of ſome Aſtrologers, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would make a Law againſt it, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times was done in the Senate of <hi>Rome;</hi> but would he be content all Divines ſhould be ſilenced, becauſe ſome are Knaves, and prate non-ſenſe, and ſo conſequently conclude no verity or truth in <hi>Divinity?</hi> Truly might I be worthy to adviſe that High Court; in the ſtead of condemning and prohibiting this moſt worthy ſtudy, they would do well to prohibit <hi>all ſuch Pamphleters,</hi> which without either feare or wit, undertake to condemne what they are ignorant of; and that none ſhould be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to condemne, or falſely undertake to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any Art or Science whatſoever, without firſt before the publiſhing of their writings, to make appear to the world, that they are throughly verſt and read in the Art they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to condemn. And this would not onely be a diſcouragement to the ignorant traducers of Arts, but alſo an incouragement to all ingenious ſpirits, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to knowledge,<note place="margin">Knowledge, the onely diſtinction between a man and a beaſt.</note> which is the onely thing that diſtinguiſheth men from bruit beaſts. For I dare confidently affirme, that if either of theſe two <hi>zealous time-ſervers,</hi> knew the depth and ground of Aſtrologie, they had never thus enviouſly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169799:59"/>
at it; <hi>The verity whereof, as alſo it's legality, I dare undertake to defend, not onely againſt what they can ſay againſt it; but alſo all the Divines in</hi> England <hi>(put together to helpe them) can imagine or contrive to ſay.</hi> But to return to our buſineſſe in hand, Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> on his four-fold argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, brings this concluſion, <hi>that God worketh not by the ſtars as ſecundary cauſes, but</hi> Ephe. 1.11. <hi>he ruleth all things after the counſel of his divine wil.</hi> O rare Divine! which underſtands not the meaning of the Holy Ghoſt better in this place, then becauſe God ruleth all things af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the counſel of his own will; he worketh not by cauſes: then, to what purpoſe I pray you are Armies, and the ſucceſſe ſometime this way, ſometime that, till in concluſion the victory is fully obtained on one ſide or other? will he ſay, (notwithſtanding the various ſucceſſe of the buſineſſe in time of the warre) that it was not concluded in the counſel of Gods own wil, that the victory ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on that ſide? ſure he will not be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious: yet you ſee he worketh it by inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. (Many of the like inſtances might be here produced, but for brevities ſake) but he might underſtand this place of Scripture to ſpeak of the Omnipotency, and Omniſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the wiſedom and power of God, in the Government of the world, (as to any one that peruſeth the Chapter will appear) will
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169799:59"/>
he therefore deny that God worketh by cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or meanes? Sure this were obſtinate wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, or abſolute madneſſe; but that he worketh by the Stars, what he preordained,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. <hi>2.</hi> of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</note> is clear from what hath been already ſayed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here againe to rehearſe, would but increaſe this ſame volum to a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſize then my firſt intentions; wherefore I leave you to look back to what hath been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aboveſaid, and haſten to his ſecond frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous reaſon or argument.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Wherein his objection touching the diverſity of Twins, is refelled. As alſo ſome other quirks againſt Aſtrologie examined and convinced.</head>
                  <p>HIs ſecond Argument or reaſon <hi>againſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie</hi> is, (ſaith he) <hi>from cleare expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in Twins conceived at the ſame inſtant, and borne in the ſame houre or leſſe.</hi> Now Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> had done well to have made this <hi>his cleare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> as cleare to his Reader, by demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration or example, and not to content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with his bare word, this is but one <hi>Doctors</hi> opinion; but will he ſay that all Twins are conceived at the very ſame inſtant of time?
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169799:60"/>
ſure he will not; but admit ſome are, yet will he not affirme, they are therefore borne in the ſame inſtant of time; I will appeale to any one of diſcretion and underſtanding in ſuch matters, if it hold with reaſon, that two Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould be borne both together; and to make it more cleare, that all Twins are not conceived at one and the ſame inſtant of time,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle, Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Cardanus, Dodoneus, Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius Gordoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us and Paraeus.</note> I refer him to the peruſal of thoſe he finds in the Margent; but let me aske him what he thinketh of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Proconeſia,</hi> who as the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry goes, lying with her Maſter, and his man her fellow ſervant both in one day; conceived by both, and brought forth one Child like the Maſter, and the other like the man. Wherefore the firſt part of his argument is not available; neither (upon good conſideration) will his following words; for he confeſſes himſelfe that the neareſt time of their birth is, in the ſame hour or leſſe, when all that knows any thing in Aſtrologie, knows that four minuts of time in the birth, gives near upon a yeares time in directions; wherefore certainly when he made ſuch clear experience in the birth of Twins, they were not born at the ſame inſtant, but at leaſt four and four and four minuts dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, for the neareſt time he confeſſes, may be <hi>ſomewhat leſſe then an houre;</hi> which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169799:60"/>
muſt breed very much difference in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; wherefore except he could have proved that they were born both at an inſtant, or giue us an example of any ſuch that he hath made <hi>cleare expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">His argument concerning Twins, Meerly ſophiſtical.</note> his argument and reaſon is a meer ſophiſtical ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. And whereas he alleageth for this ſtrength of his cavil, that <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Zara</hi> did put forth themſelves interchangeably in one hour; but how he can prove it was in one hour, is I beleeve too hard a taske for him to do, he having no Warrant therefore, from the word of God. But all this is nothing to the point, for though <hi>Zarah</hi> put forth his hand firſt, and for diſtinction had a red thread tyed about it, yet be plucked it back again, and <hi>Pharez</hi> was born before him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. Therefore I am confident he cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that <hi>Zarah</hi> was a whit the nearer his birth by putting forth his hand, for we ſee to the contrary; wherefore then how this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion maketh againſt Aſtrologie, let the weakeſt capacity judge. And this is not ſo weak, but he can bring the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne Aſtrologie,<note place="margin">The example of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> no wiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent.</note> which is far weaker (if poſſible) and ſerves as little for his purpoſe (when he rightly conſiders it) he will ſay himſelf.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169799:61"/>
For all that is acquainted with that ſtory in the Scripture, knowes that <hi>Eſau</hi> was borne firſt, and after him came his brother <hi>Jacob;</hi> and that this is cleare, the Scripture further ſayeth, the younger ſhall ſerve the elder, <hi>Ergo,</hi> they were not born at one inſtant of time, and therefore I may very well conclude, that this cavil ſerveth no whit to the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Aſtrologie; ſince for ought he can prove to the contrary, (or any one can tell) they were born many hours diſtant, and ſo conſequently they muſt needs have ſeverall ſignificators at their birth, which will cauſe very much diverſity of manners, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, forme and ſhape, &amp;c. but if he will tell me there was ſo ſmall difference in the time, as that <hi>Jacob</hi> had hold on his brothers heel; I ſay that yet notwithſtanding, doth this prove them to bee borne at one and the ſame time; but that there was ſo much time betwixt their births, as may cauſe much difference in moſt matters of their lives: but admit this objection, any underſtanding man knows it could no wiſe ſtand either with the ſafety of the Mother or Child, that he ſhould be thus born with one hand before all the body.<note place="margin">His reaſon againſt Aſtrologie, in the matter of Twins, proved frivolous and inconſiſtent with either time or reaſon.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſince it is no wiſe poſſible in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that Twins
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169799:61"/>
ſhould be born both at the ſame inſtant of time; this his frivolous cavil is of no uſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly brought for the matter in queſtion; and altogether inconſiſtent with reaſon.</p>
                  <p>But this by the way; we come to his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> which he ſaith, by reaſon of their differences, confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Aſtrologie:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">But who ſo would be farther ſatisfied in the matter of twins, let him look <hi>Ranzovius</hi> in his book <hi>De certitudine Aſtrologiae ſcientiae.</hi>
                     </note> But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the difference appears, I believe he knows not; however, if he could prove all the difference that poſſibly could be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, yet is not this a ſufficient ground for him to condemn <hi>Astrologie,</hi> ſith it hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with Divine providence, or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters beyond the common courſe of nature; which may evidently appear, that this birth of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> is, by the ſtory of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, which you may ſee was abſolutely a thing beyond the power of nature; for their mother <hi>Rebecka</hi> (the Scripture telleth us) was barren: Wherefore this being ſo, this I ſay alone, is enough to ſilence all that he can ſay againſt <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> by this example of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi> But ſure, notwithſtanding, if one ſhould particularly examine their lives, one ſhould hardly find ſuch great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them as could juſtly be alleadged to condemn Aſtrologie; for if we look to their
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169799:62"/>
                     <hi>qualities,</hi> they were both <hi>Princes,</hi> if to the number of their <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Philo</hi> his anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                     </note> look into the Antiquities of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and you will find their children were alike in number <hi>within one,</hi> and we know that <hi>Jacob</hi> had <hi>Leah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 36.</note> 
                     <hi>Rachel, Billa</hi> and <hi>Zilpah,</hi> to his Wives, 4. and <hi>Eſau, Baſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah, Mahalah Adah</hi> &amp; <hi>Aholibamach,</hi> 4. alſo; if we againe looke to their <hi>Riches</hi> or wealth, they were both ſo abundantly wealthy, as that <hi>one Country was not able to containe them both:</hi> but if any one ſay, they differed in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their <hi>birth-right,</hi> I anſwer, that this ſimple objection is of no validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">Aſtrologie med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not with Divine matters nor with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret wil of God.</note> for, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide or premonſtrate, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know the cauſe of Divine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, neither the ſecret will of God, which that this was Gods ſecret will, there is none but knows; for, as he was choſen to be the root or foundation of Gods people; ſo by the obtaining of the birth-right of his brother, did clearly premonſtrate, both this his election and the power of his ſeed, to exceed the power of the others ſeed, being the elder: And here I may alſo add, <hi>they were both roots and foudations of two great Nations;</hi> but as this maketh neither <hi>for,</hi> nor <hi>againſt Astrologie,</hi> being a ſupernatural birth;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169799:62"/>
yet it may and doth ſerve very fitly to ſhew, that if Mr <hi>Homes</hi> be minded to cavil, here is matter enough for him: Wherefore you ſee clearly, this reaſon (or non-reaſon) and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of twins, againſt <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> to be of all reaſons and examples the moſt weake, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the matter in queſtion.</p>
                  <p>So that rather I may juſtly ask him here, <hi>where is the ſtrength of his reaſons and arguments againſt Aſtrologie? where is his victory over the Aſtrologians? where is Aſtrologie proved incertaine? where hath he proved the incertainty thereof?</hi> then for him to ask (upon theſe his bald reaſons) <hi>where then is the verity or certainty of Star predictions? where is the verity of Aſtrologie?</hi> as if he had obtained an abſolute conqueſt, over <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> and <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers:</hi> And therefore concluding theſe his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be moſt invincible, and not able to be anſwered by <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> he anſwereth them himſelf his own way, in the behalf of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers. <hi>It may be</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they will read us a lecture of difference from magnitudes and motions,</hi> which anſwer I muſt confeſſe ſutes juſt well enough with the queſtion, neither of them both being fully to any purpoſe; but to be farther ſatisfied herein, let him looke <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> lib. 3.<note place="margin">Looke <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> Lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi> of his <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dripartite,</hi> to know the reaſons of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in Twins.</note> chap. 7. of his <hi>Quadripar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite,</hi> where he ſhall be clearly taught the reaſons
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169799:63"/>
of differences in Twins, and convinced of his erroneous cavill, that they are born at the ſame inſtant of time; it is not from magnitudes or motions, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what might be ſaid thereon, and that ſo much, as that I believe would trouble him to anſwer; but let that paſſe, and hear how he queſtions and anſwers for and againſt <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers, if ſo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be leſſe then the earth according to</hi> Keckerman <hi>at leaſt twenty times, and the reſt of the Planets below the ☉, as ♀ twenty ſeven times leſſe then the Earth, and ☿ twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two times, how then ſhall theſe at any poſture, at one and the ſame time effect or ſignifie any thing to all the world?</hi> it is the opinion indeed (and with very much reaſon) of all the <hi>Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> and <hi>Astrologers</hi> that ever writ, that theſe three Planets under the <hi>Sun</hi> are leſſe then the earth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Ptolomy, Albotegnius, Alfraganus, <hi>&amp;</hi> Tycho.</note> but amongſt the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of them there is much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute of the certaine magnitude thereof; but how equivalent this querke is againſt <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> is wonderful! A candle is not able to give light to a bowle, or any thing as big as a peck, becauſe it is ſo much bigger then the candle; when we know and commonly ſee that it will give light to a great ſpacious roome, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times bigger then it ſelf; (a ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon indeed) we know and ſee, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169799:63"/>
of a Planet extends it ſelf ten thouſand times beyond its viſible light to our ſight; but to come cloſer to the matter, hath not the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, ☿ and ♀, their ⚹, <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, <g ref="char:trine">△</g> dexter and ſiniſter, and ☍, to all and every part or utmoſt parts of the heavens (that are millions of times big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then both them and the earth) according to their ſeveral motions? and hath not theſe aſpects as much power and influence, as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular ☌? and whereas he asketh, <hi>what is the difference of natures in Twins? when the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Planets are proportionably bigger then the Earth,</hi> but ſure he never read that part of <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> which I before cited, concerning the ſeveral ſignificators in Twins, which is the onely cauſe and reaſon that can be given for his fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous quirke: but as he queſtions to bring his bald arguments about; ſo he anſwers his own queſtions in hopes to confirm them; <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>this is becauſe of the ſwift externall violent motion of the Stars, why then I againe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, how the Stars can have time to make any diſtinct impreſſion by any particular influence on one borne, eſpecially on one who perhaps may lie in the mouth of the womb partly borne, partly unborne; for a quarter or half an hour, or many hours; when the motion of the Zodiack is</hi> 60 <hi>times</hi> 60 <hi>miles in an houre, which is</hi> 60 <hi>miles compleat in one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to anſwer to this weake cavill, I ſhall
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169799:64"/>
ſay no more, but that though the Heavens be ſo ſwift, yet in compariſon of us it is not ſo much as an inch is to 10000 miles; for we ſee by dayly experience, that the ☉ (who is alſo by the ſame vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence (contrary to his own natural courſe) carried in like manner) doth not as to us move at all in two or three hours; for marke how ſmall a thing in a Diall gives this 60. miles in a minute, ſo that this doth no whit at all hinder the influence of the Starres, if they ſhould be hurried ten times ſwifter; for this great courſe is in relation to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the heavens, not of the earth: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides we know that thoſe ſignes that are of longer aſcenſions, as are, ♋, ♌, ♍, ♎, ♏, ♐, are ſometimes an hour and a halfe, nay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps two hours aſcending, or in the firſt Houſe, and ſo conſequently may be in any Houſe.</p>
                  <p>And for his <hi>long continuance of the Infant in the mouth of the wombe,</hi> this may ſomewhat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell, but there is no Aſtrologer that will take that part of a birth, or the beginning of the mothers travell, to be the ground or <hi>Radix</hi> of the infants <hi>Nativity;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">When the Radix of a nativity is properly to be taken.</note> but that inſtant in which He or Shee is <hi>perfectly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from the wombe, and entred this elementary world,</hi> ſince no man can proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169799:64"/>
call that a birth, which is but half a expelled, or but halfe perfected, when alſo ſometimes the Infant may draw back again.</p>
                  <p>So that theſe frivolous kind of cavillings, is neither available nor indeed any thing in the leaſt to the controverſie in diſpute; yet Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> is willing to help Aſtrologers to anſwer theſe his <hi>feeble queſtions,</hi> with far wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker expreſſions; and to ſay the truth, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance it ſelfe, <hi>for</hi> ſaith he, <hi>If Aſtrologers will plead and thing to helpe themſelves herein, from the ſlowneſſe of other motions of the Stars, that are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to them,</hi> viz. <hi>that the fixed ſtars, move with ſo ſlow a motion from North to South back againe, as that their courſes are not finiſhed in leſse then</hi> 7000. <hi>yeares;</hi> Now I would very faine know of any rational man, how this anſwer of his in the behalfe of Aſtrologers, is able to availe them a ruſh, or himſelf in his purpoſe, ſince they are alſo hurried with the like violence as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, every 24. hours once about the earth? but as all theſe his quirks are brought into his advantage (as he thinks,) ſo the advantage he ſtrives to gain hereby, he may brag of, as much as of the former; for all this his gaine is but the opportunity of this queſtion, viz. <hi>How then can any age ſince the beginning of the world have experence, what the conjunction of the Starres may produce?</hi> This is a great Conqueſt indeed, but how ſlender an Artiſt he herein renders
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169799:65"/>
himſelf, let the judicious judge, ſince it is moſt certain that theſe ſtars we call fixed, move not at all; <hi>Ergo,</hi> are nominated fixed, for they move unanimouſly together in their ſphere, which is about 7000. years finiſhing its courſe, <hi>not the Stars;</hi> but ſuppoſe they do move, yet they move not by ſeveral motions, as the one being flower or ſwifter then another, for they are all alike diſtant each from other continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and if theſe come not to aſpect nor ☌ of the Planets; yet the Planets come to configu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with them, as ♄ commeth in configu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them once in 29. years ſome odd months and dayes; ♃ in 12 years, ♂ in three years, ☉ in one year or twelve months; ♀ and ☿ in the like time or there abouts, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in 28 dayes and ſome odd hours. I hope then <hi>this experience</hi> may be learned in a far ſhorter time then 7 or 8000 years, and if the motions of the Planets are not exactly for ever calculated by Aſtronomers in former ages, and that of late to our hands, I would faine Mr. <hi>Homes</hi> would do them better; and ſince theſe is ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and vulgarly known, it is ſufficient ground for any one to take the exact poſition of the heavens, either in Twins births or any others, without the error that theſe motions he ſpeaketh of can cauſe, which indeed is none at all. Wherefore if theſe aſſertions of his, be not weaker then all his former cavils, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169799:65"/>
moſt apparently inconſiſtent with what he would faine prove, I leave to the learned and judicious herein to judge, and haſten to his remaining cavils.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Wherein his indeavours to prove Astrologie of no truth or certainty, as alſo it's rules and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, are themſelves of leſſe truth, or ground, nay and indeed ſenſleſs.</head>
                  <p>HIs third Argument againſt Aſtrologie is, to prove the <hi>Maximes, Theorems, Axiomes</hi> and <hi>Canons of the Art, inconſiſtent with truth or foundation;</hi> but firſt he denyeth abſolutely any ſuch (<hi>viz.</hi> ground or principles) at all to be in the rules of Aſtrologie, but with what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent <hi>falſehood, malice,</hi> and <hi>invective wickedneſs,</hi> this is done, ſhall appeare to the world by theſe examples following, being ſome few queſtions and reſolutions, which by my own experience I can againſt all malicious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries affirme to be moſt punctually true; wherefore I have thought good here to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge them to the world, that ſuch envious carpers at this moſt true Art, may be for ever ſilenced, or at leaſt that their perverſeneſs may be apparently and vulgarly knowne in their
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169799:66"/>
colours; but ſee how inveterately they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it, notwithſtanding milions of the like examples, which they know not otherwiſe what to ſay for themſelves, unanimouſly (this ſurpaſſing the natural capacities of their profound judgements, when they ſo clearly ſee themſelves by experience convinced) they preſently ſay, <hi>it is impoſſible this ſhould be true! ſure this is very ſtrange? nay I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident this could not be done by Art! this is a plaine dealing with the Devil!</hi> it is witchcraft! and the like ſimple and malicious cenſures, or rather ſcandals hereon, but to the buſineſs intended.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Die ♃ <hi>10.</hi> Ian. <hi>1649 10.</hi> h. <hi>0.</hi> m. <hi>P. M.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. a. <g ref="char:trine">△</g>. ♀. ad. ⚹. ♃. Shall I receive my money? and when?</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:169799:66"/>A Gentleman a very good friend of mine (having expected ſome money from an Vncle of his, a Fathers brother, and being diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed two ſeveral returnes of the Poſt; being therefore doubtfull of the receipt thereof) propounded unto me this queſtion. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I erected this Sceame, it being the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall time of his queſtion.</p>
                  <p>I find here but two degrees aſcending, and that of the ſigne ♎, which according unto the rules of ſome <hi>Aſtrologians,</hi> and indeed all that ever I met with) ought not to be judged on; <hi>yet I agree not alwaies with them in this point, nor in many more beſides this.</hi> The reaſon then I take this queſtion to be ſufficiently ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall, is, becauſe it ſo exactly diſcribeth the Querents body, together with his marks; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the queſtion concerned not the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, but the ſecond Houſe, and there is 24. degrees aſcending, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But to be ſhort, I find ♃ here ſignificator of the Querents Uncle (from whom this money in queſtion is expected) as being lord of the third from the fourth, yet the ſixth in the figure, he is located in the Querents ſecond, intimating therefore his intention and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to performe the Querents deſire; which judgement was the more confirmed by being in ⚹ with ♀, Lady of the Querents ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; as alſo ♂ lord of the ſeventh, which
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169799:67"/>
is the Uncles ſecond in a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> to the Querents ſecond Houſe; and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeparating from a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> of ♀ and immediately applying to a ⚹ of ♃ in the ſecond, both being friendly aſpects and principle ſignificators, (though ſhe ſeparated not from ♃ and applyed to ♀, yet they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both fortunes, and her application was to ♃ in the querents, 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>) I judged as aboveſaid, that his Uncle had a great willingneſſe to performe his deſire, and that he ſhould receive the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney he expected, of the which I was the more confirmed, by reaſon I found ♁ diſpoſed of by ♀ and that within a fortnight after the time of the queſtion; the reaſon I nominated juſt that time, was, for that ♃ and ♀ lackt juſt two degrees of the perfect ⚹ aſpect; ♀ indeed as ſhe is in a moveable ſigne, might denote but dayes; yet by reaſon ♃ is in a fixed ſigne, which might ſignifie months, or yeares (but as the ancients teach, <hi>a te et a ſcientia</hi>) I tooke the <hi>medium</hi> therefore of theſe extreams, which was weeks; which accordingly happened, and not till then: for on the 25th. day of the ſame moneth he received it, notwithſtanding by a Letter preſently after the queſtion, a ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner time was nominated, and after that, not above four dayes before the day I nominated, came a meſſenger from his Uncle, about other buſineſſe to him, and yet brought it not, which did ſeeme very ſtrange to the Querent.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169799:67"/>
This Gentleman<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>viz.</hi> the Querent, till his acquaintance with me, had but a weake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of <hi>Aſtrologies legality</hi> or <hi>veritie;</hi> I believe he is at this preſent in this Town, and can juſtifie this for a truth.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe ſome ignorant traducers of this Art, do affirme that <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> will never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake (nay and that they cannot) to reſolve the querents doubts, without he comes to them with a great belief of their skill, and of the power of the Art; I will here give you my judgement on two figures, propounded not onely by unbelievers, but enemies of <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie;</hi> which were propounded by way of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and in their arguing with me of the verity of <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The occaſion of this Queſtion was thus; upon ſome conference, of the <hi>verity</hi> of this Art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> we here undertake in this ſmall Treatiſe to Vindicate: a Gentlewoman of very long acquaintance with me, being then in company was very invective againſt it, inſomuch ſhe would no wiſe believe any one could reſolve her any thing ſhe ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and wondred I would maintain (in the leaſt) the verity thereof; whereupon I deſired her to propound any queſtion to me; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe told me that ſhe was confident if there were any verity therein, yet I could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve her queſtion; her reaſon was, becauſe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169799:68"/>
no <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> (ſhe told me) would undertake to reſolve <hi>an unbelieving querent:</hi> ſo that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired then the willinger to be demanded ſome Queſtion, the rather, for that I was deſirous to convince her, of this weake opinion; but to be ſhort, ſhe at length after much intreaty, propounded this Queſtion, as followeth.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>☿. 19. <hi>Decem</hi> 1649. 4. h. 30. m. <hi>P. M.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 
                        <hi>a. ⚹. ☉. ad</hi> ⚹. ♂.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shall I receive the money due from the Parliament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I find here the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſignificatrix of the querent in ♏ diſpoſed of by ♂ and he lord of the 11; whereupon I told her, ſhe depended much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169799:68"/>
a friend (or ſo in pretence) which might happily be a ſouldier, which I was the more confident of, by reaſon I ſaw <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> going ſtraight to the ⚹ of ♂, but becauſe ſhe ſeparated laſt from the ⚹ of ☉ lord of the ſecond; and ſo transferring the light of ☉ to ♂, I told her I feared her friend was not very faithful unto her, but did under-hand ſeek to defraud her of what ſhe expected of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or of as much as in him lay he could do: I found alſo ♃ ſignificator of the <hi>Parliament</hi> diſpoſed of by ♂, as alſo ☉ lord of her ſecond, ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from a ⚹ of ♃, I acquainted her they had lately promiſed her faire, but ſtill (I told her) I did believe her martiall friend did obſtruct their good willingneſſe unto her, and becauſe I ſaw ♂ ſo very near the <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> aſpect of ♃, and that he was diſpoſed of by ♂, I told her I was confident (notwithſtanding all the faire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes (of which ſhe confeſſed ſhe did plentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abound) the Parliament had lately made unto her) he or ſome man or men ſignified by ♂ would be her hinderance, ſo that ſhe ſhould no wiſe receive the money ſhe expected of them, which was the more certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by his being in ☍ to the cuſpe of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
                  <p>She thereupon confeſſed that the friend ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by ♂ (whom I deſcribed) was indeed very forward (to outward appearance) to do
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169799:69"/>
for her, but ſhe had indeed (of late) found him very perfidious, but yet ſhe ſaid ſhe could not be perſwaded but the intentions of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> were reall: but not long after (<hi>viz.</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three moneths, as ♂ wanted three dayes of the <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> of ♃) came forth the <hi>Ingagement,</hi> which her husband refuſing to take, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to loſe his debt: <hi>and who was the authors of the Ingagement?</hi> which when ſhe alſo found ſo marvellouſly to happen, ſhe was ſo converted from being an antagoniſt or enemy to <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> that ſhe became a great lover and admirer thereof; often times ſince blaming her former raſhneſſe in condemning what ſhe was ignorant of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:169799:69"/>But another example that the querents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, is no whit material to the perverting of the Artiſts judgement, I will alſo here give you; for if the queſtion be indeed radical, the <hi>Artiſt</hi> having any skill, and not deviating from his rules, he ſhall ſeldome faile.</p>
                  <p>And this is of an incredulous Gentlewoman alſo; her Queſtion was, of her husband being abſent.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>♂. 17. <hi>Oct.</hi> 1648. 9. h. o. m. A. M. <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. <hi>a</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:trine">△</g>. ☉. <hi>in</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:trine">△</g>. ☿. <hi>ad</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:trine">△</g>. ♀.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Where is my husband? And when will he returne?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:169799:70"/>This Queſtion was propounded by a Lady very unbelieving in the Art of Aſtrologie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that if poſſible, ſhe exceeded the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
                  <p>I find here ♀ ſignificatrix of the abſent huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and located in the twelfth houſe of the figure; whereupon I told her, her husband was in Priſon (but before (becauſe ♏ aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) I deſcribed his ſhape, as alſo the markes of his body) who when ſhe heard this, with much admiration began to tell me, he was indeed in Priſon, and was ſuch a manner of man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly as I had deſcribed him; but ſhe could never have believed this could have been told her, which was the reaſon ſhe would ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to me of his condition; whereupon ſhe was very deſirous then to know farther, <hi>viz. when ſhe ſhould ſee him;</hi> but firſt I finding <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from ☉ (by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> aſpect) lord of the ninth, yet the third, from the ſeventh his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant; &amp; in <g ref="char:trine">△</g> of ☿ lord of the tenth in the figure, and then immediately transferring the light of both by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> to ♀, the abſents ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, I accquainted her that a brother or kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his, ſhould make means to ſome officer in great authority, or the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral (for it could not then be the King) which ſhould be the means of his inlargement,<note place="margin">He was then himſelf a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</note> and for that theſe aſpects were ſo near the time, that the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:169799:70"/>
queſtion was demanded, I told the querent I was confident her husband was already or ſhould ſuddenly be inlarged, and be relieved alſo with money; which I ſaw alſo by ☿ his being in combuſtion of ☉ he was in want of; as for the time when ſhe ſhould ſee him, I find ♀ very near the aſcendant, and the ſame time ſhe comes to the cuſpe thereof, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> comes to the ſame degree (or very near it) of ♊ the proper aſcendant of <hi>London,</hi> I told her I was confident when ♀ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> came to theſe places, he would be with her, which was the 25. day of the ſame moneth, being Wedneſday, which accordingly happened; and when I came to the ſpeech of him, he confeſſed all that I had related concerning him was to the letter true; viz. <hi>That he was in Priſon ten weekes, and was by the means of his brothers power with the Generall (which was then Sir</hi> Thomas Fairfax) <hi>he had his liberty, and that his brother did (for his neceſſary occaſions) furniſh him with</hi> 20. <abbr>l.</abbr> I could here inſert many the like examples, but ſince they are ſo frequently divulged in other Treatiſes, I hold it here no wiſe neceſſary longer to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; but Mr <hi>Homes</hi> I pray, if one had asked <hi>whether a man had lived with his wife or no?</hi> or <hi>whether he loved another mans wife?</hi> might not theſe queſtions have been reſolved as well as any of theſe above mentioned?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:169799:71"/>But let us ſee how he can prove <hi>the rules or principles of the Art groundleſſe and of no verity;</hi> and firſt (he ſaith) <hi>becauſe of the foreſaid various varieties and uncertainties of the Stars, both in their own motions, and in compariſon with others,</hi> but you have alſo afore received a confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe aſſertions of his, and therefore this his firſt reaſon is not one jot equivalent to his purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Becauſe no man knoweth the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar qualities of the Stars,</hi> but this is but one Doctors opinion, and therefore I may as wel, and with as good reaſon and ſtrength of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument deny his words, and not ſhew him to the contrary; but this were to deceive my Reader <hi>Homes like.</hi> And with this word only he cannot be willing to content himſelf, but he muſt ſtrive to confirm it by his falſe allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; <hi>No Artiſt yet ever undertook to ſpeake of more then the ſeven Planets, and ſome few nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated fixed ſtars, of ſome few ſeveral magnitudes;</hi> with what ſlight expreſſions are theſe his ſcandalous allegations vented,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Looke</hi> Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus <hi>Coperni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi> &amp;c.</note> when it is clear and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent to the world, that all thoſe Stars from the firſt magnitude down to the ſixth magnitude, and even to the cloudy
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169799:71"/>
and occult Stars as they call them, are made clear unto us, and the whole world,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>And for their natures, looke</hi> Ptolomy, 1. <hi>Quadripartite,</hi> Cap. 8. Stadius, Sconerus, <hi>and</hi> Lucas Gauricus</note> whoſe works are ſo apparently extant, and yet ſo openly traduced and ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; what will he not then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to hide that is not ſo apparent? he doth not onely deny here neither ſo apparent a truth, but affirmeth as palpable an untruth in his very next words; they leave out ſaith he, or are <hi>ignorant of millions of Stars, that are neither named nor known.</hi> What non-ſenſe &amp; ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity doth this his hatred aganiſt <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> cauſe him to be guilty of? <hi>I would very fain know how he came to know theſe millions of Stars that he ſaith were never yet knowne or named? he knowes that that was never knowne,</hi> ſure he did not learn this great skill in <hi>Bredſtreet,</hi> truly theſe ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous whimſies, makes me beleeve he is not well in his ſenſes, ſince he was in the ſtreet aforeſaid, and cauſes me alſo extreamly to <hi>Pitty the poore Paſtor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>Thouſands of Stars cannot be ſo much as ſeene a minute together, as the Philoſophers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in their diſcourſe of</hi> Via lactea, <hi>the milkie way in the heavens, to be ſeene in a moſt ſtarry night, eſpecially in Winter.</hi> Before he was up with his <hi>millions,</hi> now he is come down to his <hi>thouſands,</hi> I am confident at the laſt he wil deſcend to his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169799:72"/>
                     <hi>unites;</hi> yet here alſo may his Reader ſee how he ſtrives to deceive and delude him with vain conceits, and to take effect the better, he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers them on the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> I beleeve his <hi>Philoſophers</hi> will deſcend to be ſome whimſical <hi>Poets.</hi> For the <hi>Poets</hi> indeed fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that on a day <hi>Ganimedes</hi> who (as they ſay) was <hi>Jupiters</hi> Cup-bearer,<note place="margin">Of <hi>Via lactea;</hi> or the milkie way.</note> carrying his Lord a ſack Poſſet or a cup of Milke, ſtumbled in in the way at ſome great fixed Star (or at the paw of the Beare) and let fall all his liquor, which ever ſince hath cauſed the heavens to be in that place white or cloudiſh even in the moſt clear nights, but perhaps if <hi>Canis major</hi> and <hi>minor</hi> had been called on,<note place="margin">Then <hi>M. Homes</hi> had not had this <hi>Via lactea</hi> to have prated on.</note> it had been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; I may then with as good reaſon or ground conclude this ſtory, as true as his allegation, that they are <hi>an innumerable company of ſmal ſtars that cannot be diſcerned or diſtinguiſhed;</hi> but I would very fain underſtand this paradox, <hi>that they cannot be ſeen, and yet they are knowne to be an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Stars,</hi> ſure he hath a very diſcerning eye, and rather one ſurpaſſing his judgement, for he but even now, knows more <hi>then all people ever yet knew,</hi> and <hi>now he ſeeth what was never yet ſeen:</hi> but theſe or any ſuch whimſical expreſſions or arguments, are enough to fright the ignorant
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169799:72"/>
from the beliefe, either in the verity or legali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Aſtrologie; he cares not how little he troubles them with reaſon or truth.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Becauſe all the Stars do ſhine on the earth at once joyntly and promiſcuouſly, ſo that they that are under them cannot by any rule from nature know what influences ſhall be predominant in their effects.</hi> But to anſwer this frivolous objection in every particular by plain proof, were too tedious here to relate, ſince for the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſtudents herein, there hath been whole volumes writ, to whom I ſhall refer all that require farther ſatisfaction then what I here do ſay, which is onely thus, that to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine either generall or particular effects, it is not alwayes neceſſary to conſider all the Stars, for ſome never are ſeen in our horizon, and of thoſe that are, half are ever under the earth, and of thoſe that are above the earth, many are in ſuch places of the heaven, as they are of little or no uſe in our ordinary practice: Wherefore he moſt weakly aſſerteth this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſince as I ſaid before, their vertues and natures are ſo plainly delivered us by the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and thus with ſuch like frivolous and weak arguments and ſuppoſitions, he indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to confirme his objection againſt <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> and its rules, as alſo <hi>that the complexions of people may be altered from their child-hood to their man-hood; and that there are cauſes between us and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169799:73"/>
the Stars to alter their influence; and that Aſtrologers depend upon Clocks and Dials to know the ground of their workes, which Clocks and Dials may faile, and ſo conſequently needs muſt the Aſtrologer:</hi> and ſuch ſimple cavils not knowing what indeed to object, for certainly all that knows any thing in the world, muſt needs judge this kind of arguing to be meerly either for want of matter, or to patch up a ſimple diſcourſe: for what can hereby in the leaſt, or all that he doth farther rabble hereon be ſaid, to prove Aſtrologicall rules uncertaine; ſurely this is no more to the purpoſe, or to our diſpute in hand, then for me to ſay <hi>I will,</hi> when one aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me <hi>if Aſtrologie be lawful or no?</hi> or any ſuch ridiculous anſwer: But ſince in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this preceding diſcourſe, all theſe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the reſt of <hi>his ſophiſtications,</hi> are already anſwered; I hold it moſt vaine longer here to dwell, but haſten to his fourth and laſt argument againſt <hi>Aſtrologie:</hi> for <hi>our diſpute is not to decide quicks and quillets, but anſwer thoſe objections that are brought to prove the vanity and falſeneſſe of Aſtrologicall Predictions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:169799:73"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Wherein he thinketh the ground of the Art wholly ſhaken and overthrown, by affirming it meerly imaginary, <hi>viz.</hi> the ninth and tenth ſphere, and in them the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> therein proveth and ſheweth his own ignorance the more apparently manifeſt.</head>
                  <p>BUt what doth this ſophiſticall cavil availe him, to the ſubverſion of the verity or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> when the motions &amp; effects of the Stars are known? but even as wel may he condemn the rules, &amp; precepts of all Arts which are alſo gathered by experience and reaſon, as <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> becauſe the ſignes of the <hi>Zodiack</hi> are deviſed by men; but the reaſon they attribute theſe names, as <hi>Aries, Taurus, Gemini,</hi> and the like, to the conſtellations of the heaven is by reaſon of their formes and particular vertues expreſſed under theſe figures;<note place="margin">Ptolomie, 1. <hi>Quadripartite.</hi>
                     </note> for <hi>Ptolomy</hi> hath delivered the nature of the particular Stars in them by themſelves, as alſo their <hi>particular complexions</hi> and <hi>efficacies,</hi> as alſo the <hi>Houſes, exaltations, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicities, termes</hi> and <hi>faces,</hi> and other <hi>dignities,</hi> of the ſignes, as they follow the nature of the <hi>Planets:</hi> and ſince theſe are known, to what end are all theſe his cavils whether there be a
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169799:74"/>
ninth or tenth ſphere? for let there be none at all (as he ſaith) nor any thing called a <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack</hi> (as he would faine perſwade the world) yet ſince clear experience and practice evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him, as alſo demonſtration that there are ſuch conſtellations (call them what you will) his ſophiſticall weake argument will no wiſe ſerve his turne; for I may as well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there is a <hi>Dog</hi> a <hi>Bear,</hi> both leſſer and bigger a <hi>Swan,</hi> a <hi>Crown,</hi> a <hi>Wagoner</hi> and the like, as he denieth there is not a <hi>Bull</hi> a <hi>Ram</hi> or a <hi>Lion in the heavens,</hi> when it is not deſired litterally (by any <hi>Aſtrologer</hi>) to be underſtood. Wherefore I leave him here to bait <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſa major</hi> with <hi>Canis major</hi> and <hi>minor,</hi> till I am of his weak opinion, or till he can perſwade any judicious ſoul to believe this his doctrine: and haſten to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this our diſcourſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Wherein the confutation of the objections that are brought for <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is examined and refel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</head>
               <p>THere remains nothing more to be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Mr <hi>Homes</hi> his diſcourſe, but his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futations</hi> (as he cals them) <hi>of the objections that are brought for Aſtrologie;</hi> which indeed is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169799:74"/>
refelled in what hath been already ſaid; having conſideration to the definition of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie,</hi> and the Tenents of <hi>Aſtrologers:</hi> but becauſe I will not give him occaſion to carpe or brag of my leaving him here, I ſhall go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him in every particular of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining cavils; that ſo the reader may ſee on what ſmall grounds he builds up his tower of oppoſition againſt <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> and what ſmall reaſon he hath to carpe thereat.</p>
               <p>Firſt he ſaith <hi>Melancthon</hi> ſtandeth not for <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>1.</hi> Sect. <hi>6.</hi> Chap. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. <hi>2.</hi> of this diſcourſe.</note> but you have heard before how he alſo thus falſely abuſed St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Galen;</hi> but admit neither of all theſe were one jot for it, but poſitively againſt it; yet will not this (if granted) make a whit againſt <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> ſince he will not deny but theſe are men, and <hi>humanum eſt errare, man is ſubject to frailty and errour,</hi> and therefore is not Aſtrologie abſolutely condemned hereby; ſince already you have heard it no wiſe condemned by the word of God,<note place="margin">Chap. 3. of this Treatiſe.</note> but the effects of the Stars clearly thereby manifeſted; yet for the anſwer of this his deluſive quirke, I ſhall onely ſend him to <hi>Melancthon</hi> to be better peruſed, (which here to clear would be too too tedious) and then he will not thus inconſiderately wrong him, as the other two St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:169799:75"/>
the reaſon whereof was alſo a negligent peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to gain-ſay (as he thinks) <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>that ſome make a great matter of the Star that was ſeen at the birth of Chriſt:</hi> But I anſwer, that this appearance of this Star maketh neither for nor againſt Aſtrologie, ſince as before you have heard <hi>Divine matters are not to be judged by naturall cauſes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 4. Sect. 1 and Chap. 4. Sect. 2.</note> and all the world knows what manner of Birth Chriſts was, <hi>viz.</hi> of a Virgin, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of a man, this is rather a Miracle then a Naturall Birth, and <hi>Miracles alſo are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore excluded from the power of the Stars:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his quirkes of the nature of it, as alſo whether it be naturall or ſupernaturall, or whether it belong to <hi>Meteorologie</hi> or <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> muſt needs fall: and the wiſe men might well enough, (who could diſtinguiſh between a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and a ſupernatural Star) know it fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told the Birth of the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> when by all fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Propheſies the like and ſame was Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted and pointed out.</p>
               <p>But to come to the objections Logicall, which he ſaith are brought in defence of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> and his anſwers, the firſt is, that <hi>God made the Stars to be ſignes,</hi> Gen. 1.14. <hi>therefore the knowledge of the ſignification of theſe ſignes are lawfull:</hi> his anſwer is, <hi>God made them to be
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169799:75"/>
ſignes of natural effects or events, not of arbitrary and morall, that depend on mans will.</hi> Wherefore here firſt the reader may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that Mr <hi>Homes</hi> doth now (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what he hath all this while denyed) confeſſe the Stars to be ſignes of naturall effects and events,<note place="margin">Nota bene.</note> and whereas he denies them to be ſignes of arbitrary and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall events depending on the will, he gaineth little of the Aſtrologer, who as you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready heard acknowledgeth the ſame. Where is then the confutation of Aſtrologie, or the objections brought for it? it is the abuſe of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> he meaneth, yet me thinks a wiſe man ſhould have diſtinguiſhed between the lawfulneſſe of an Art, and the abuſe thereof; ſhall any man be counted rationall that ſhall deny Religion to be, or that there is none lawful, becauſe there are abuſes therein? this is a ſtrange way of condemning an Art.</p>
               <p>To handle here every particular objection and his anſwers hereon, would be too tedious, and indeed but vaine, and to little purpoſe, ſince he can ſay no more then what hath been already (if rightly underſtood) anſwered: for to inſiſt upon every vaine quillet (as is moſt of his diſcourſe) were an <hi>Herculean labour,</hi> and to render my ſelf more weak then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounders or authors thereof; wherefore with this text I conclude; <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.4. onely I ſhall
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169799:76"/>
here make ſome <hi>Queries</hi> to the judicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My fiſt Quere is, whether the beſt of Arts and Sciences hath not been in one age or other ill thought on, and by ſome ignorant therein, moſt vildly tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traduced, as alſo the very word of God it ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, Whether the denying or writing againſt an Art, be a ſufficient condemnation thereof, or proof of the illegality of it? (which to conclude or grant, were to deny the Scripture, ſince it alſo hath by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts and ſuch like been cenſured.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, Whether the warrant from Scripture, the Fathers, the Learned, and experience; be not a ſufficient warrant for the lawfulneſſe of an Art?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly, Whether Aſtrologie be not thus (if with diligence thou haſt peruſed this diſcourſe) warranted and up-held.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly, Whether it may not then be practiſed by the beſt of Gods people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly, Whether an Art that hath the word of God, experience and reaſon on it's ſide, be a Doctrine of Devils or Diabolical?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſeventhly and laſtly, whether ſuch ignorant traducers of ſo noble and worthy an Art, are not Diabolical teachers, and deſerve exemplary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thus to deny and gain-ſay truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whoſo is delighteed in ſuch like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, let him peruſe that exquiſite piece of Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi> lately publiſhed; wherein Aſtrologie is clearly proved by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Demonſtrations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:169799:76"/>And likewiſe to that ſhort (but full) piece, of <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> Vindicated, newly publiſhed: Both ſold at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For truly I know not whether I have rendred my ſelfe more weak in the Vindicating of ſo apparent a a truth, then theſe</hi> puny Antagoniſts <hi>thereunto have in striving to Eclipſe the glorious ſplendor thereof, in ſo much that let them henceforward, (or any one elſe) perſiſt in this vaine way of condemning truth; I ſhal take as ſlight notice thereof, as of a Dogs barking at a ſtranger whom he knoweth not: for did they know what they condemn, they would not render themſelves ſo ridiculous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thought here to have concluded this <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,</hi> but as I was upon cloſing, appeares a <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet</hi> from one <hi>John Raunce,</hi> who had formerly put out a Declaration againſt <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> yet declared himſelf more ſimple therein then at this time I will make known, yet becauſe in <hi>my reply</hi> thereunto, he (as well as ſome others that was not well acquained with his ſcope or intention therein, or what ſmall reaſon he had for the writing of his ſimple <hi>Pamphlet</hi>) found fault with ſome words I had therein againſt him; I thought good here, both for his and their better ſatisfaction, to give them the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of my expreſſions againſt him. Yet in a Letter I ſent him the ſame reaſons which I here relate in anſwer to a part of a Letter I received from him, wherein he hath theſe words, <hi>Your
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169799:77"/>
Pamphlet is nothing to the purpoſe, being ſo full of expreſſions of hatred againſt me;</hi> to which I ſay, I returned him this anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> that this was the worſt I was confident he could ſay of it, yet if he better conſidered it, he would find it deſerved not altogether this raſh condemnation;<note place="margin">A Vindication of the Authors reply to <hi>Raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> Declaration againſt Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</note> for, firſt I ſaid nothing but what I proved: and ſecondly, I play with him at his owne weapon; I wil begin with the latter, and would know of him, if I have not as good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to call him an inſtrument and child of the Devil, as he calleth the profeſſors of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, <hi>inſtruments of the Devil, Page</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 11. of his ſcandalous <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> and if in any place I call him <hi>Idiot</hi> (as in the third Page of my <hi>reply</hi> to his Declaration) it is for concluding his cavil as granted, before he either brought proof or reaſon for it; and in ſo doing, let any one or himſelfe judge, what he rendereth himſelfe to be: and in my ſixth Page perhaps I call him <hi>Dunce;</hi> I pray is it without cauſe, when hee telleth mee hee was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Practitioner in Aſtrologie, and yet he is ſo ignorant of the rules thereof, as that he imagineth them to be Diabolical? upon which conſideration (as I remember) in the ſame place, I call him <hi>Shallow-braines,</hi> and alſo at the lower end of the Page <hi>Foole,</hi> to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169799:77"/>
condemne what he neither underſtood nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, which if he had, he would have ſhewed by his arguments (which was no wiſe to the purpoſe, but onely his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits and words) wherefore I thought good to acquaint the Reader herewith, that ſince nothing is therein ſpoken without reaſon or proof, they might not be ſo tranſported with negligence, to conclude or condemn <hi>my reply</hi> without better conſideration then a meer ſlight view thereof.</p>
               <p>And ſince in that Letter he ſent me, he chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth either my ſelfe or any, or all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Art of Aſtrologie, to convince him by argument or reaſon; he may perhaps expect I ſhould ſay ſomething to his latter diſcourſe (which is more weak and ſimple then his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) which ſince I have been of late acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his quality, I ſhall not trouble my ſelf further, nor indeed my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but with this word,<note place="margin">I leave it to him ſelf to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ultra crepidam,</hi> let <hi>not the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler go beyond the laſt,</hi> or let no man meddle with what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his reach or capacity; yet leſt I ſhould have given the <hi>vaine-Coxcombe</hi> cauſe of boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by my ſilence.<note place="margin">Aliquid latet quod non patet.</note> I have by the laſt Carrier ſent him an anſwer (in a Box) to his ſimple pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, with a Letter, a Copy of which that the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169799:78"/>
vulgar may not be ignorant of, as alſo that they may not be led away by the weak cavils of ſo ſophiſtical a <hi>Jack;</hi> I here commend unto their view. For indeed there is an old proverb yet true (though a homely one) which cauſes me take no more notice of him, being of that <hi>quality</hi> he is of, <hi>Stir in a — and it wil stinck the worſe.</hi> For had I had the relation of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my <hi>Reply</hi> to his nonſenſe, I had never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalued my ſelf to have appeared his Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt, but had buried both him &amp; his brat in perpetual ſilence; what he is and was, you ſhal here have, as was ſent to Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> by a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that knows his former and preſent way of living.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Copy of a Letter ſent by me, to <hi>John Raunce.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Ars non habet inimicum niſi igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantem. Nemo poteſt artem judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, niſi Artifex.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ne ſutor ultra crepidam. <hi>William Rameſey.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die ☿ 4. Decemb. 1650.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:169799:78"/>
            <head>A Copy of a Letter ſent to Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> by a Gentleman in the Country.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Doubt not but you have ſeen a tract written by one <hi>Raunce</hi> of <hi>Chippin Wickham</hi> where I live, which <hi>Raunce</hi> did formerly profeſſe himſelf to have been a ſervant unto you, but you denyed it before my ſelf and ſome Aldermen which were with me, at which he was much troubled; the tract is againſt <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> but it is very wittily anſwered by one Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Rameſey,</hi> and that you may the better know this <hi>Raunce,</hi> I ſhal tell you what he hath been, and what he is, he hath been a Shoomaker, and I think he did twice break, and had he not been of the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rameſey</hi> had wronged him extreamly in calling him Mr. <hi>Raunce;</hi> he confeſſes he hath often ſpoken with the <hi>Devil</hi> and that is very likely; for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes being at work he would ſuddenly hit ſhooe and tools out of the window, and run the Devil knew whither for the ſpace of one, two or three weeks ſome times together, but not thriving by Cobling, he came to <hi>Wickham</hi> and taught Children to write and read, and after that he practiſed of a ſudden Phyſick and Chyrurgery, and ſo continues, but a pittiful ignorant ſneaking fellow; a fellow that goes not to Church,
<pb facs="tcp:169799:79"/>
cryed up by ſome ſort of people, eſpecially the weaker and more factious ſort, one of <hi>Sedgewicks</hi> tribe as Mr. <hi>Rameſey</hi> ſtiles him; one which to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, being to diſcourſe of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> could not give any diſtinction of it, but onely <hi>that it was a ſpeaking of the Stars:</hi> ſome of his Companions and he are about to anſwer Mr. <hi>Rameſey,</hi> if they do, I deſire all Artiſts ſhould take notice what he is, and judge of him accordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thus with my hearty loving reſpects to you, I reſt your loving friend.</hi> J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
